Troy, 你別再說謊了
Troy, you ought to stop that lying.
我沒有說謊
I ain't lying.
那個黑人藏著個這麼大的西瓜
Nigger had a watermelon this big,
還說: 什麼西瓜, Mr. Rand?
talking about, "what watermelon, Mr. Rand?"
我真想上前跟他對質, 還"什麼西瓜, Mr. Rand?"
I'd like to fell out. "What watermelon, Mr. Rand?"
那個西瓜就大大的放在那
And it sitting there, big as life.
- 那Mr. Rand說了什麼?   - 他沒說什麼
- What Mr. Rand say?   - He ain't said nothing.
他知道, 如果這個黑人那麼愚蠢
He figure, if the nigger was too dumb
不知道自己在藏著一個西瓜
to know he's carrying a watermelon,
他也不能跟他說道理
he wasn't going to get much sense out of him.
他把那大西瓜藏在他的外衣下
Trying to hide that great, big, old watermelon under his coat.
害怕讓那些白人看到他偷回家
Afraid to let the white man see him carry it home.
我像你一樣, 我沒有時間跟這種蠢人相處
I'm like you. I ain't got no time for them kinda people.
告訴我, 為何那個人看起來那麼生氣
Now, what he look like getting mad
在他看到從工會來的人跟Mr. Rand說話之後?
'cause he seen the man from the union talking to Mr. Rand?
他上前跟我說
He come up to me, talking about
Troy Maxson早晚會讓我們失去工作的
"Troy Maxson gonna get us fired."
我跟他說:別跟我說這個
I told him, "get away from me with that."
他一邊走一邊說你是專門製造麻煩的人
He walked away from me calling you a troublemaker.
Mr. Rand怎樣說?
What Mr. Rand say?
他沒說什麼, 只叫我
He ain't said nothing. Told me to go down
下星期五到理事長的辦公室, 停下!
to the commissioner's office next Friday. Whoa!
他們叫我去那裏會面
They called me down there to see them.
你一天還在投訴當中
Well, as long as you got your complaint filed,
他們就不能辭退你
they can't fire you.
那是一個白人跟我說的
That's what one of them white fellas tell me.
我才不擔心他們會辭退我
I ain't worried about them firing me.
就因為我問了個問題, 他們就要辭退我?
What, they gonna fire me 'cause I asked a question?
我只問了個問題
That's all I did.
我問Mr. Rand
I went to Mr. Rand and I asked him.
我問他: 為何?
I asked him, "why?
為何你讓所有白人負責駕駛, 而有色人種就去搬運?
Why you got all the white mens driving, and the colored lifting?"
跟他說:什麼事了? 我不重要嗎?
Told him, "what's the matter? Don't I count?
你以為只有白人才夠聰明去駕駛嗎?
Think only white fellows got sense enough to drive a truck?"
該死的, 那又不是寫文件, 任何人都懂駕駛
"Hell, that ain't no paper job. Anybody can drive a truck.
你為何讓所有白人駕駛, 而有色人種去搬運?
"How come you got all the whites driving and the colored lifting?"
他回答我: 去跟工會說吧
He told me, "take it to the union."
該死的, 我就去投訴
Well, hell, that's what I done.
而現在他們就想說一堆謊話隱瞞過去
Now they want to come up with this pack of lies.
我跟Brownie說了, 如果那些人向他查詢
I told Brownie if the man come and ask him any questions,
就即管告訴事實
just tell the truth.
這只不過是因為你投訴了
Ain't nothing but somebody trumped it up on you
所以有人要誣蔑你
'cause you filed a complaint on.
Brownie沒那麼聰明
Brownie ain't got that much sense.
他什麼事也不去想
Man wasn't thinking about nothing.
我只想他們改正職位描述
All I want them to do is change the job description,
給所有人一個機會去駕駛, 開車
give everybody a chance to drive the truck. Oi!
Brownie沒想過這, 他不是很聰明
Brownie can't see that. He ain't got that much sense.
你怎麼知道他一直在跟
How you figure he be making out
Taylor的酒吧裏那個女子調情?
with that gal, be up in Taylors' all the time?
- 那個叫Alberta的女子   - 誰?
- That Alberta gal?   - Who?
Brownie.
我跟他經常在一起, 就像我們一樣,
Same as you and me, getting about as much as we is.
- 心照不宣吧   - 是嗎?
- Which is to say nothing.   - It is, huh?
我想你比我更猜得透他吧
Well, I figure you doing a little better than me.
我不會跟你說我在猜什麼
And I ain't saying what I'm doing!
朋友, 聽著, 我太瞭解你
Nigger, look here. I know you.
難怕你只接近了她一點
If you had gotten anywhere near that gal,
二十分鐘後你就想跟誰說了
20 minutes later, you'd be looking to tell somebody.
而你第一個想要分享的對象
And the first one you gonna want to tell,
想要吹噓的對象就是我
that you gonna want to brag to is going to be me.
我不會這樣做
Oh, I ain't saying that.
我看到你在偷看她
I see where you be eyeing her.
我所有女人都看, 我不會錯過任何女人
I eye all the women. I don't miss nothing.
別聽別人說...
Don't never let nobody tell you
Troy Maxson不看女人
Troy Maxson don't eye the women.
你顗覦她呢
Hey, you been doing more than eyeing her.
你請她喝酒了
You done bought her a drink or two.
天啊, 我是請過她, 那又如何?
Hell, yeah, I bought her a drink. What that mean?
我也請過你喝酒
I bought you one, too.
那算什麼, 就因為我請她喝了一杯?
What that mean, 'cause I buy her a drink?
我只是出於禮貌
I'm just being polite.
你請她喝一杯完全可以
It's all right to buy her one drink.
那就是出於禮貌
That's what you call being polite.
但當你繼續請她喝酒
But when you want to be buying two or three,
那就是顗覦
that's what you call eyeing her.
聽著, 你認識我這樣久了
Look here. As long as you've known me,
你有聽過我去追求女人嗎?
you ever known me to chase after women?
當然有, 一直認識你以來你都有
Hell, yeah! Long as I've known you.
你忘了我認識你多久了
You're forgetting, I knew you when.
我在說在我跟Rose結婚後
I'm talking about since I been married to Rose.
噢...那倒沒有
Oh... not since you been married to Rose.
我可以說, 那倒是真的
That's the truth, though. I can say that.
明白了吧, 沒什麼可說
All right then. Case closed.
我在Alberta的房子外看見過你
I see you be walking up around Alberta's house.
那種時候你應該在Taylor的酒吧才對
You supposed to be at Taylors',
而你卻在那裏出現了
and you be walking up around there.
你為何在意我去哪?
What you watching where I'm walking for?
我也沒在意你去哪
I don't be watching after you.
不, 我看見你在那裏不只一次
No, I seen you walking around there more than once.
當然, 我們經常在一起
Hell, you liable to see me walking anywhere.
你看到我在那裏不代表什麼
That don't mean nothing 'cause you seen me walking around there.
她從哪來的?
Where'd she come from, anyway?
她就好像突然出現一樣
She just kinda showed up one day.
塔拉哈西, 你看到她
Tallahassee. You can look at that
就知道她是來自佛羅里達州 [塔拉哈西是其首都]
and tell she one of them Florida gals.
那裏的女人都亭亭玉立
They got some big, healthy women down there.
就像樹一樣高大
Grow them right up out of the ground.
她有印度人的血統
She got a little bit of Indian in her.
很多在佛羅里達州的黑人都有印度人血統
Most of them niggers in Florida got some Indian in them.
我不知道她是不是混血兒
Yeah, I don't know about that Indian part,
但她真的很高大
but she damn sure big and healthy.
要是讓她穿上長襪
Woman wears some big stockings.
再張開她那雙誘人的腿, 真棒
Got them crazy big legs, and hips wide as the Mississippi river.
雙腿並不重要
Legs don't mean nothing.
它們只會在做愛時阻礙你
You don't do nothing but push 'em out of the way.
但是臀部可重要了
But them hips,
它們坐在你上面時軟呼呼的
they cushion the ride.
Troy, 不能這樣算
Troy, you ain't got no sense!
那是真的, 像你年輕做愛時一樣
It's the truth. Like you riding on goodyears!
你們在這裏都在聊什麼了?
What you all out here getting into?
女人, 你為何在意我們在聊什麼?
What you worried about what we getting into for, woman?
這是男人之間的討論
This is men talk.
我又怎麼會在意呢?
What I care what you all are talking about?
Bono, 你要留下來吃晚餐嗎?
Bono, you gonna stay for supper?
不了, 謝謝, Rose
No, thank you, Rose,
Lucille說她今晚要煮豬腳
but Lucille say she cooking up a pot of pigfeet.
豬腳? 那我也跟你回去了
Pigfeet? Hell, I'm going home with you.
要是你家煮豬腳, 我甚至會在你那睡一晚
I might even stay the night, you got some pigfeet.
Rose, 你裏面有煮什麼比豬腳還棒的嗎?
You got something in there to top them pigfeet, Rose?
我在煮雞肉, 今晚吃雞肉和羽衣甘藍葉
I'm cooking up some chicken. I got some chicken and collard greens.
那你先進去繼續烹調
Well, you go on back in the house.
讓Bono和我繼續剛才的話題
Let me and Bono finish what we talking about.
這是男人之間的討論, 我待會也有些事要跟你討論
This is men talk. I got some talk for you later.
你也知道我要說什麼的
And you know what kind of talk I mean, too.
你先進去準備下 [指做愛]
You go on in there and powder it up.
Troy, 夠了!
Troy, stop it!
噢, 來吧, 女人
Oh, woman, come here.
Bono, 聽著
Oh! Look here, Bono.
我第一次看到這女人時
When I first met this woman,
我就行動了
I got out that place there.
我準備好我的馬匹
Hitch up my pony, saddle up my mare
因為那裏有個女人在等著我
there's a woman out there for me somewhere
我到處找尋她的蹤影
I looked at here, looked at there,
然後看到Rose時我就徹底被她迷住了
saw Rose, and I latched on to her.
我想也沒想就上前跟她說...
I latched on to her and I told her...
我來告訴你當時到底發生了什麼事
Now, I'm gonna tell you the truth.
我跟她說: 寶貝, 我不想要結婚
I latched on to her and told her, "baby, I don't want to marry.
我只想成為你的男人
"I just want to be your man."
Rose回答我... 你來告訴他, Ro
Rose told me... Tell him what you told me, Ro.
我跟他說如果他不打算長相廝守
I told him if he wasn't the marrying kind,
那就滾開, 別擋著那些想的人前來
then move out of the way, so the marrying kind could find me.
她真這麼說了: 朋友, 你在擋著我
That's what she told me, "nigger, you in my way.
你在阻擋我的視線
"You blocking the view.
滾開, 讓我找我的愛人
"Move out the way, so I can find me a husband."
- 我想了幾天    - 你才沒有
- I thought it over 2-3 days.   - Two-three days, nothing.
你那晚就回來了
You was back the same night.
我回來並跟她說: 好吧, 寶貝
I come back, told her, "okay, baby,
但我要買一隻矮腳公雞 [比正常公雞小, 但好鬥]
"but I'm gonna buy me a banty rooster
把它放在後院裏
"and put him out there in the backyard.
當它看到陌生人
"And when he see a stranger come,
它就會到處跑跟大聲啼叫
"he gonna flap his wings and crow."
Bono, 看這裏, 我看著前門就夠煩了
Look here, Bono. I done watched that front door by myself.
我擔心的是[她的]後庭
It was that back door I was worried about.
Troy, 別說了, 你在撒謊
Don't talk like that! Troy, you're not but telling a lie.
但是我們結婚後才發現
Only thing was, we first got married,
忘了那公雞吧, 因為我們根本負擔不起後院
forget the rooster. We ain't had no yard.
我也明白
I hear you tell it.
Lucille和我以前住在Logan街 [美國, 丹佛]
Me and Lucille was staying down there on Logan street.
我們有兩間房子, 還有個廁所在後院裏
Had two rooms with the outhouse in the back.
我平常都不介意的
I ain't mind the outhouse none.
但當冬天時有陣該死的冷鋒吹過
But when that goddamn wind blew through there in the winter,
我就恨死它了! [以前家裏沒有水管]
that's what I'm talking about!
直至今天, 我還在想
To this day, I wonder why the hell
為何我會住在那裏六年之久
I ever stayed down there for six long years.
我當時也不知道可以怎辦
But, see, I didn't know I could do no better.
我以為只有白人才配有室內廁所什麼的
I thought only white folks had inside toilets and things.
很多人也像這樣
A lot of folks don't think
安於現狀
they can do no better than they're doing now.
那是些要改變的想法
Just something you gotta learn.
就像很多人還去Bella的店買東西
A lot of folks still shop at Bella's.
Bella賣的東西沒問題啊, 她賣的食物也很新鮮
Ain't nothing wrong with Bella's. She got fresh food.
我不是在說她賣的食物有沒有問題
I ain't said nothing about if she got fresh food.
我在說她賣的價錢
I'm talking about what she charge.
同樣的貨品她比A&P賣貴十美分
She charges 10 cents more than the A&P.
A&P沒為我做過什麼
A&P ain't never done nothing for me.
我會選擇消費在我認為對的地方
I spend my money where I'm treated right.
我到Bella的店裏說
I go down to Bella, say,
我要買一條麵包, 星期五付錢, 她就給我了
"i need a loaf of bread, I'll pay you Friday," she gives it to me.
如果我還在
What sense that make when I got money
其他地方消費
to spend it somewhere else
把這個賣人情給我的人忘掉, 我還算什麼?
and ignore the person who done right by me?
聖經裏沒教人忘恩負義
That ain't in the Bible.
我們不是在談論聖經
We ain't talking about what's in the Bible.
明知道她賣貴了, 還在那買東西, 這樣理智嗎?
What sense it make to shop there when she overcharges?
那你去你想去的地方買
Well, you do your shopping where you want to,
我去賣過人情給我的地方買
I do my shopping where people been good to me.
噢, 我只是不認同她賣貴了而已
Oh, I don't think it's right for her to overcharge, that's all.
聽著, 我該走了
Look here, I got to be getting on.
Lucille都要發怒了
Lucille gonna be raising all kind of hell.
朋友, 你要去哪, 我們還沒喝完這瓶呢
Where you going, nigger? We ain't finished this pint.
先喝完吧
Come here finish this pint.
我會留下啊, 如果你請我喝的話
Well, hell, I am, if you ever turn the bottle loose.
我唯一要感謝A&P的地方
Only thing I'll say about the A&P is,
就是他們讓Cory在那工作
I'm glad Cory got that job down there.
幫補一下他的開支
Help him with his school clothes and things.
Gabe搬走了, 我們有點捉襟見肘
Gabe done moved out, things getting tight around here.
他有份工作
He got that job,
至少可以照顧下自己
he can start to look out for himself.
Cory被一間大學的美式足球隊錄取了
Cory done got recruited by a college football team.
我跟他說過大學的美式足球隊到底是怎麼一回事
I told that boy about that college football stuff.
那些白人不會讓他碰美式足球的
The white man ain't gonna let him get nowhere with that football.
他第一次來我就跟他解釋過了
I told him when he first come to me with it.
現在你告訴我他更著迷了
Now, you come telling me he done got more tied up in it.
他該去車行工作
He ought to get recruited in how to fix cars,
還是做點能令他過活的事
or some way he can make a living.
他不是想成為職業美式足球員
He ain't talking about making no living playing football.
那只是他的興趣而已
It's just something the boys in school do.
他們會派負責人員來
They're gonna send a recruiter by
跟你商討, 他會跟你說
to talk to you. He'll tell you.
他不是想成為職業美式足球員
He ain't talking about making no living playing football.
被錄取是個榮譽
It's an honor to be recruited.
他不會走得遠的, Bono就懂
It ain't gonna get him nowhere, Bono'll tell you that.
如果他跟你一樣那麼有運動細胞, 他會成為偉大的球員
If he be like you in sports, he gonna be all right.
這麼久以來只有兩個人打棒球比你好
Ain't but two men ever played baseball good as you.
就是Babe Ruth和Josh Gibson [皆為著名棒球員]
That's Babe Ruth and Josh Gibson.
他們就是唯一比你有更多全壘打的人
Them the only two men ever hit more home runs than you.
打棒球給了我什麼? 我沒有地方上廁所
And what it ever get me? I ain't got a pot to piss in,
又或者靠此買過一間房子
or a window to throw it out of.
時代不同了, Troy
Times have changed since you were playing baseball, Troy.
你打棒球都是戰爭之前了, 很多事情都改變了
That was before the war. Times have changed a lot since then.
有什麼改變了?
How the hell they done changed?
現在很多有色人種都在球隊裏
They got a lot of colored boys playing ball now.
棒球也好, 美式足球也好
Baseball and football.
Ro, 你說對了, 時代不同了, Troy
You right about that, Ro. Times have changed, Troy.
你只是生不逢時而已
You just come along too early.
世上沒有所謂"生不逢時"
There ought not never have been no time called "too early."
以他為例...
Now you take that fellow...
那個以前在洋基隊
What's that fellow they had playing
當右外野手的叫什麼?
right field back then for the Yankees?
Bono, 你該記得的
You remember who I'm talking about, Bono,
在洋基隊當右外野手的那個
played right field for the Yankees.
- Selkirk?    對, 就是他 [George Selkirk]
- Selkirk?   - Yeah, Selkirk, that's it!
他的職業生涯打擊率是.269, 你看得出了嗎?
Man's batting 269, you understand? 269!
那合理嗎? 我的打擊率是.432, 有37個是全壘打
What sense that make? I'm batting 432 with 37 home runs!
他的打擊率才.269, 卻在洋基隊裏當右外野手!
He's batting 269, playing right field for the Yankees!
我昨天看到Josh Gibson的女兒
I saw Josh Gibson's daughter yesterday.
她穿著破爛的鞋到處跑
She's running around with raggedy shoes on her feet.
我敢打賭Selkirk的女兒
I bet you Selkirk's daughter ain't running around
可不是穿著什麼破爛的到處走
with no raggedy shoes on her feet. I bet you that.
現在很多職業棒球員都是有色人種了
They got a lot of colored baseball players now.
Jackie Robinson是第一個
Jackie Robinson was the first.
Jackie Robinson都是名星了
Folks had to wait for Jackie Robinson.
我看過無數比Jackie Robinson還會打棒球的黑人
I done seen 100 niggers play baseball better than Jackie Robinson.
我甚至看過Jackie Robinson都進不了的球隊
Hell, I seen some teams Jackie Robinson couldn't even make!
還說什麼Jackie Robinson?
What you talking about, Jackie Robinson?
Jackie Robinson只是個無名小卒而已!
Jackie Robinson wasn't nobody!
我要說的是如果你會打球
I'm talking about if you could play ball,
他們就該給你機會
then they ought to let you play.
而不是在意你的膚色人種
Don't matter what color you are.
還說我生不逢時
Come telling me I come along too early.
如果你會打球, 他們就該給你機會
If you can play, then they ought to let you play.
你再繼續這麼喝會死的
You gonna drink yourself to death.
不用喝那麼多吧
You don't need to be drinking like that.
噢, 死神而已, 我都見過了
Oh! Death ain't nothing. I done seen him,
還跟他搏鬥過, 不用你來跟我說
I done wrestled with him. You can't tell me nothing about death.
死神不過是個外角的快速球
Death ain't nothing but a fastball on the outside corner,
而你知道我有什麼能耐
and you know what I do with that.
Bono, 看這裏, 我有在說謊嗎?
Look here, Bono, am I lying?
你扔個到腰水平高度的快速球
You get one of them fastballs about waist high
從外角扔過來
on the outside corner of the plate
那簡直易如反掌
where you can get the meat of the bat on it,
老天啊, 我會把它打到出場外
and, good god, you could kiss it good-bye.
- 我在吹噓嗎?    - 不, 你在說事實
- Am I lying?   - No, you telling the truth.
我親眼看見過
I seen you do it.
如果我在吹牛, 那會是天大的謊話
If I'm lying, that's 450 feet worth of lying.
死神來我來說就是這麼回事
That's all death is to me.
一個從外角扔來的快速球
A fastball on the outside corner.
我不知道你為何說起死亡了?
I don't know why you want to get on talking about death?
說說又沒有問題
Ain't nothing wrong with talking about death.
那是生命的一部分啊, 每個人都必經
That's a part of life! Everybody gonna die.
你會死, 我會死
You gonna die. I'm gonna die.
Bono會死, 天啊, 所有人都會死
Bono gonna die. Hell, we all gonna die.
但你也沒必要繼續說吧
But you ain't got to talk about it.
我不喜歡說這種事
I don't like talking about it.
那是你提起的
Well, you the one brought it up.
Bono和我剛才在說棒球
Me and Bono talking about baseball.
你突然說我會喝死
You come telling me I'm gonna drink myself to death.
不是嗎, Bono?
Ain't that right, Bono?
你知道我一周只有一晚去喝酒
Now you know I drink just but one night out the week,
那是星期五晚
that's Friday night.
我不會喝多
I drink just enough to where I can handle it.
然後我就會離開, 不碰它了
Then I leaves it alone. I cuts it loose.
所以你不必擔心我會喝死
So, you ain't got to worry about me drinking myself to death
因為我不害怕死亡
'cause I ain't worrying about death.
我見過他, 跟他搏鬥過
I done seen him, done wrestled with him.
跟你說, Bono
Look here, Bono.
我有天看到死神舉軍衝向我
I look up one day, and death is marching straight at me,
像是閱兵時的士軍隊一樣
like soldiers on parade.
當時死神大軍在衝向我
The army of death was marching straight at me.
當時是1941年7月中
It was the middle of July, 1941.
然而卻像冬天一般冷
And it got real cold, just like it be winter.
那時候死神他啊
And it seemed like death, himself,
好像舉手碰了我肩膀一下
reached out and touched me on the shoulder.
他像我現在碰你一樣, 我感受到那寒意
He touched me like I touch you now. I got cold as ice.
死神就站在那裏, 對我露出不友善的笑容
Death standing there, grinning at me.
Troy, 別說了
Troy, why don't you hush that talk.
我說: 死神先生, 你想要什麼? 要帶走我嗎?
I said, "what you want, Mr. death? You be wanting me?
你不再派你的小卒來了嗎?
"You done sent your army to be getting me?"
我直直的看著他
I looked him dead in the eye.
我什麼都不怕
I wasn't fearing nothing.
我準備跟他鬥個你死我活, 直至現在我都是!
I was ready to tangle, just like I'm ready to tangle now!
聖經說要經常警惕
Bible says be ever vigilant.
所以我不會喝醉, 我還要耳聽八方
So, I don't get but so drunk. I got to keep watch.
Troy當時進了慈善醫院
Troy was right down there at mercy hospital.
你記得他那次得了肺炎
You remember he had that pneumonia,
還有發燒, 躺在床上還說些有的沒的
laying there with a fever, talking plumb out his head.
當時死神站在那盯著我
And death standing there, staring at me,
手握著鐮刀
carrying that sickle in his hand.
終於, 他說: 你想再活多一年嗎?
Finally, he say, "you want to be bound over for another year?"
他這樣說
Just like that. He say,
你想再活多一年嗎?
"you want to be bound over for another year?"
我說: 去你的, 我們現在就說清楚
I said, "bound over, hell! We can settle this right now."
他聽了後退後了點
He kinda fell back when I said that.
我即時龍精虎猛
And all the cold went out of me.
我伸手搶去他的鐮刀
I reached down, I grabbed that sickle.
我用盡力氣扔走它
I threw it as far as I could throw it,
然後我們開始埋身肉搏
and me and him commenced to wrestling.
我們打了...六...三天三夜
We wrestled for... Carry the six... Three days and three nights!
我不知道從哪兒來的力量
Now, I don't know where I got the strength from,
因為他處於優勢時
'cause every time he tried to get the best of me,
我重新振作
I reached way deep down inside myself,
並又得到對抗他的力量
found the strength to do him one better.
Troy每次說起這事
Every time Troy tells that story,
都有不同的版本
he find different ways to tell it,
不同的謊話
different things to make up.
我沒有胡說, 女人
I ain't making up nothing, woman.
我在說實話
I'm telling you the facts of what happened.
我跟死神搏鬥了三天三夜
I wrestled with death for three days and three nights,
而現在還能站著跟你說話
and I'm standing here to tell you about it.
繼續, 在最後
All right. At the end of the third night,
我們都脆弱得站不起來了
we done weakened each other to where we can't even hardly move.
死神突然站起來
Death stood up.
他披上那連帽的白色袍子
He threw on that robe, had a white robe with a hood on it.
他披上後便去尋找他的鐮刀
He throwed on that robe and ent off to look for that sickle.
他說: 我會回來的, 像這樣
He said, "I'll be back." Just like that. "I'll be back."
我說: 是嗎? 那你得好好找我
I said, "yeah? Well, you gonna have to find me!"
我又不是傻子
I wasn't no fool.
我不會自找麻煩的
I wasn't going looking for him.
我知道死亡不是拿來開玩笑的事, 他早晚會找上我
I know death ain't nothing to play
with. And I know he's gonna get me.
我知道我早晚要加入他的大軍
I know I got to join his army, his camp followers.
但我一天還有力氣
But as long as I keep up my strength and see him coming,
還能保持警覺
as long as I keep up my vigilance,
他就得打上一場硬仗
he gonna have to fight to get me.
我不會輕易讓他帶走我
I ain't going easy.
那你看, 既然你要保持警覺
Well, look here, since you got to keep up your vigilance,
讓我替你拿著那酒瓶
let me have the bottle.
該死的, 我不應該告訴你那部分
Hell, I shouldn't have told you that part.
我應該刪掉那部分
I should have left out that part.
Troy一直都說這些話
Troy be talking all that stuff.
然而有一半時候他根本不知道自己在說什麼
Half the time, he don't even know what he be talking about!
- Bono會瞭解的   - 對, 我很瞭解你
- Yeah, Bono know me better than that.
- That's right, I know you.
我知道你就像Uncle Remus一樣 [說故事的人]
I know you got some Uncle Remus in your blood.
你有的故事比魔鬼擁有的罪人還多
You got more stories than the devil got sinners.
天啊, 我也跟他說過話
Oh, hell, I done seen him, too. Done talked to the devil.
沒人想知道
Nobody wants to be hearing that stuff!
嗨, 爸
Hey, pop.
你來這裏做什麼?
What you come "hey, poppin'" me for?
你好嗎, Rose?
How you doing, Rose?
Bono先生, 你好嗎?
Mr. Bono, how you doing?
嗨, Lyons, 你呢?
Hey, Lyons, how you been?
他一定過得很好
He must've been doing all right.
他整周都沒來找過我
I ain't seen him around here last week.
Troy, 放過你的兒子吧, 他特地來看你
Troy, leave your boy alone. He come by to see you
而你卻又想胡說
and you want to start all that nonsense.
我沒有說Lyons什麼, 來喝口
I ain't bothering Lyons. Here, get you a drink.
我們知道原因
Me and him got an understanding.
我知道他為何來, 而他也知道
I know why he come by to see me, and he know I know.
爸, 別這樣說, 我只是來見你一下
Come on, pop. I just stopped by to say hi,
看看你過得怎樣了
see how you was doing.
- 但你昨天沒來啊   - Lyons, 你留下來吃晚飯嗎?
- You ain't stopped by yesterday.
- You staying for supper, Lyons?
我在煮雞肉
I got some chicken cooking in the oven.
不了, Rose, 謝謝, 我剛巧經過這裏而已
No, Rose, thanks. I just was in the neighborhood
想著進來看你們一下
and thought I'd stop by for a minute.
得了吧, 你剛巧經過這
Yeah, you was in the neighborhood all right.
老兄, 你還真會說話
Nigger, you telling the truth there.
你剛巧經過這因為我今天發薪
You was in the neighborhood 'cause it's my payday.
既然你提到了, 給我$10
Well, hell, since you mentioned it, let me have $10.
該死的, 我寧願下地獄
I'll be damned. I'll die and go to hell
和魔鬼玩牌也不會給你
and play Blackjack with the devil before I give you $10.
我想知道你看見過的魔鬼
That's what I want to know about, that devil you done seen.
爸看見過魔鬼? 真會吹牛
Pop done seen the devil? You too much, pop.
- 對, 我見過   - 他才沒有
- Yeah, I done seen him. - He ain't seen no devil.
我跟他說過那男人不是魔鬼
I told him that man ain't had nothing to do with the devil.
他把任何他不明白的事, 都稱呼為魔鬼
Anything he can't understand, he want to call it the devil.
看這, Bono, 我去Hertzberger的店買些傢俱
Look here, Bono. I go by Hertzberger's to get some furniture.
收音機說三房寓所只售$298
You got three rooms for $298. That what it say on the radio.
三房寓所只售$298, 他還為此創作了首歌
"Three rooms, $298." He made up a little song about it.
我去到那, 他說我不能貸款
I get down there, man tell me I can't get no credit.
我每天都工作, 還不能貸款
I'm working every day, can't get no credit.
那怎辦?
What to do?
我只有些破爛的傢俱
I got an empty house with some raggedy furniture.
Cory沒有床
Cory ain't got no bed.
他在地上鋪點破布就睡了
He's sleeping on a pile of rags on the floor.
每天都工作, 卻不能貸款
Working every day, can't get no credit.
我回來後, Rose也看到的
I come back here, Rose'll tell you,
我非常憤怒, 想著有什麼能做
madder than hell, trying to figure out what to do.
有人來敲門
Come a knock on the door.
我才住在這裏三天, 有誰知道我在這?
I ain't been living but three days, who know I'm here?
我去應門, 原來是魔鬼
I open the door. Devil standing there.
一個大個子
Bigger than life.
一個白人, 穿著得體
White fella, got on good clothes and everything.
手裏拿著塊剪貼板
Standing there with a clipboard in his hand.
我還沒說什麼
Now, I ain't got to say nothing.
他就說了:
First words come out of his mouth,
我知道你需要點傢俱而你不能貸款
I understand you need some furniture and can't get no credit.
我都要暈倒了, 他說: 我會讓你貸款
I liked to fell over.
He said, "I'll give you all the credit you want,
但你需要付利息
"but you gonna have to pay the interest on it."
我跟他說要是他給我那間寓所
Now, I told him, he give me them three rooms,
多少都行
he can charge whatever he want.
有輛貨車第二天來了
Next day, a truck pull up here,
兩個男人給那三間房間佈置了傢俱
two men unload them three rooms.
駕車的那位給了我本書
Man what drove the truck give me a book.
跟我說每月初, 寄$10到書上這個地址
Said first of the month, send $10 to the address in the book,
那就可以了
everything'll be fine.
說如果你沒付
Said if you miss a payment,
魔鬼會來找你, 而你需要付上更多
the devil was coming back, and there'll be hell to pay.
那是15年前的事
That was 15 years ago.
直至今天, 每月初, 我都寄$10
To this day, first day of every month, I send my $10,
非常準時, Rose可以擔保
just like clockwork. Rose'll tell you.
Troy在說謊
Troy lying.
我從此沒再見過那人
I ain't never seen that man since.
你說如果他不是魔鬼會是誰?
Now, you tell me, who else that gonna be but the devil?
而我沒有賣掉靈魂什麼的
And I ain't sold my soul or nothing like that.
我不會跟坐著貨車來的魔鬼交易
No, I wouldn't have, truck with the devil over nothing like that.
但我卻換來所有傢俱, 所以我準時寄我的十塊
But I got my furniture. And I send my $10, just like clockwork.
你都付多久了?
How long you say you been paying this $10 a month?
15年
15 years.
天啊, 那你不是一早付清了嗎?
Hell, ain't you finished paying for it yet?
那人要你付多少?
How much the man done charge you?
是啊, 我一早付清了
Oh, hell, I done paid for it.
早就付清了
I done paid for it 10 times over.
事實是, 我怕我不繼續付要承擔後果
Fact is, I'm scared to stop paying.
別聽Troy說的, 傢俱是在Glickman先生的店買的
Troy lying. We got that furniture from Mr. Glickman.
他沒有每月給誰十塊
He ain't paying no $10 a month to nobody.
天啊, 女人, Bono知道我不是傻的
Hell, woman, Bono know I ain't that big a fool.
我還想說
I was just getting ready to say,
我知道有個橋下賣便宜的傢俱
I know where there's a bridge for sale.
我告訴你
I'll tell you this.
那人是不是魔鬼不重要
It don't matter to me if it was the devil.
他有沒有給我貸款也不重要
It don't matter if the devil give credit.
- 總有人要給我吧    - 那很重要
- Somebody got to give it.   - It ought to matter.
你到處說你跟魔鬼交易了
You walking around here saying you gonna make truck with the devil,
你將來得跟上帝解釋清楚
god's the one you're gonna have to answer to.
祂會作出審判
He's the one gonna be at the judgment.
聽著, 爸, 給我十塊
Yeah, well, look here, pop, let me have that $10.
我會還你的
I'll give it back to you.
Bonnie在醫院找到工作了
Bonnie got a job working at the hospital.
Bono, 我怎跟你說的?
Bono, what did I tell you?
只有這老兄有事相求時我才會見到他
Only time I see this nigger is when he want something.
只有那種時候
That's the only time I see him.
別說這, 爸, Bono先生不想聽這個
Come on, pop, Mr. Bono don't want to hear all that.
給我十塊, 我說過Bonnie找到工作了吧
Let me have the $10. I told you, Bonnie's working!
她找到工作又如何了?
What that mean to me if Bonnie's working?
我不在乎, 要是她在工作, 你就去問她拿十塊
I don't care if she working. Go ask her for $10 if she's working.
還說她在工作, 那你為何不工作?
Talking about Bonnie working. Why ain't you working?
爸, 你知道我不能找到正當工作
Ah, pop, you know I can't find no decent job.
我去哪找? 你知道我的過去
Where am I gonna get a job at? You know I can't get no job.
我說過, 我認識一些人
I told you, I know some people down there.
如果你想, 我可以讓你來清理垃圾
I can get you on the rubbish if you want to work.
你上次有事相求時我就跟你說了
I told you that last time you come back here asking for something.
不了, 爸, 謝謝, 那不適合我
No, pop, thanks, that ain't for me.
我不想替人清理垃圾
I don't want to be carrying nobody's rubbish.
我不想做這些千篇一律的工作
I don't want to be punching nobody's time clock.
怎麼了? 清理垃圾配不起你嗎?
What's the matter? You too good to carry people's rubbish?
你以為那十塊是哪裏來的?
Where you think that $10 you talking about comes from?
我就要去清理垃圾, 然後我賺的就給你
I'm just supposed to haul people's rubbish
就因為你太懶惰?
and give my money to you 'cause you too lazy to work?
你不去工作
You're too lazy to work
然後想知道你為何沒錢
and want to know why you ain't got what I got.
Bonnie在哪間醫院工作? 慈善醫院?
What hospital Bonnie working at, Mercy?
她在Passavant醫院裏的洗衣房工作 [匹茲堡醫療中心大學]
She down at Passavant, working in the laundry.
我不能給你, 我給了你十塊
I ain't got nothing as it is. I give you $10,
那我接下來一星期都吃豆嗎?
I got to eat beans the rest of the week?
不, 你不會拿到那十塊
No, you ain't getting no $10 over here.
不至於吃豆吧
You ain't got to be eating no beans.
真不知道你為何能說出這?
I don't know why you want to say that?
我沒有多餘的錢!
I ain't got no extra money!
Gabe搬走了
Gabe done moved out,
錢都替Pearl小姐交房租了
giving his money over there to Miss Pearl, paying her rent.
我們都捉襟見肘了
Things done got tight around here.
我再也不能承擔每次發薪金也給你
I can't afford to be giving you every payday.
我不是想你給我
I ain't asked you to give me nothing.
我是想你借給我
I asked you to loan me $10.
我知道你有十塊的
I know you got $10.
我是有啊, 你知道為何嗎?
Yeah, I got it. You know why I got it?
因為我到處亂花錢
'Cause I don't throw my money away on them streets.
你想過得快活, 當個音樂家
You want to live the fast life, being a musician,
有錢在俱樂部流連
running around in them clubs and things,
那就學懂照顧自己
then learn to take care of yourself.
你不會看到我請求別人幫忙
You ain't gone find me asking nobody for nothing!
這麼都年來都沒有
I spent too many years without.
你和我不同
Hey, you and me is two different people.
我吸取了教訓, 知道該做什麼
I done learned my mistake and I learned to do what's right by it.
你還想不勞而獲
You still trying to get something for nothing.
沒人欠你什麼
Life don't owe you nothing.
是你欠自己的, 問問Bono, 他也懂
You owe it to yourself. Ask Bono. He'll tell you I'm right.
我們有各自生活的方式
You got your way of dealing with the world, I got mine.
我唯一在乎的是音樂
Only thing that matters to me is the music.
看得出來, 你吃什麼不重要
Yeah, I can see that. Don't matter how you gonna eat,
哪來錢也不重要
don't matter where your next dollar coming from.
你說得真對
Yeah, you telling the truth there.
我知道我要吃飯, 但我也要生活
I know I got to eat. But I got to live, too.
我需要點什麼讓我每天有動力
I need something that's gonna help me get out of bed in the morning,
讓我感覺到我還存在
make me feel like I belong in the world.
我不打擾誰
I don't bother nobody.
我只是玩音樂而已
I just stay with my music
因為那是我生存於世的理由
'cause that's the only way I can find to live in the world.
不給就算了, 別跟我說要做什麼
Otherwise, ain't no telling what I might do.
我不是來批評你和你的生活方式
I don't come by criticizing you and how you live.
是讓你借十塊給我
I just come by to ask you for $10.
我不想聽你說教
I don't want to hear all that about how I live.
天啊, 你母親把你養得真好
Boy, your mama did a hell of a job raising you.
爸, 你改變不了我的, 我已經34歲了
You can't change me, pop. I'm 34 years old.
如果你想改變我
If you wanted to change me,
或許你該在我成長時陪伴左右
you should have been there when I was growing up.
我來看你, 向你借十塊
I come by to see you, ask you for $10,
而你卻跟我說我是如何被養育成人?
and you want to talk about how I was raised?
你根本不知道是怎麼一回事
You don't know nothing about how I was raised.
給他十塊吧, Troy
Let the boy have $10, Troy.
你在看什麼? 你知道我沒有錢的
Hell you looking at? You know I ain't got no money.
你知道我把錢放在哪
You know what I do with my money.
給他吧, 如果你想的話
Go on, give him $10 if you want him to have it.
我會, 當你交給我的時候
I will, soon as you turn it loose.
這裏
There it is.
$76.22
Seventy six dollars and twenty-two cents.
看到了嗎, Bono? 我只能拿回$6
You see this, Bono? I ain't gonna get but six of that back.
夠了吧, 拿著, Lyons
He ought to stop telling that lie. Here, Lyons.
謝謝, Rose
Thanks, Rose.
我要走了, 下次見
Look, I got to run. I'll see you all later.
等下, 你會說"謝謝, Rose"
Wait a minute. You gonna say, "thanks, Rose,"
但你不感謝付出的那個
but you ain't gonna look to see where she got that money from.
你看到他們怎對待我嗎, Bono?
You see how they do me, Bono?
我知道是你的錢, 爸
I know she got it from you, pop.
謝謝, 我會還的
Thanks. I'll give it back to you.
看, 又撒謊了
There you go, telling another lie.
你還我$10時, 你還欠著$30呢
Time I see that $10, you'll be owing me $30 more.
- 再見, Bono先生   - 保重, Lyons
- See you, Mr. Bono.    - Take care, Lyons.
爸, 謝謝, 下次見
Thanks, pop. I'll see you again.
真不知道為何他不去工作
I don't know why that boy don't go and get him a decent job
然後照顧他的女人
and take care of that woman he got.
他會找的, Troy, 那孩子還小
He'll be all right, Troy. The boy is still young!
那孩子34歲了
The boy is 34 years old.
別又開始說了
Let's not get off into all that.
我要走了, Lucille在等著我
Look here, I got to go. I got to be going. Lucille gonna be waiting.
看到這女人了嗎, Bono?
See this woman, Bono?
我愛她
I love this woman.
我愛得都有點痛了
I love her so much, it hurts.
我太愛她, 我都找不到方式表達了
I love her so much, I done run out of ways of loving her,
所以我要用回最簡單的
so, I got to get back to basics.
你星期一早上別來
Don't you come by my house Monday morning,
跟我說要上班了
talking about time to go to work.
- 因為我還撫摸她   - 夠了, Troy
- 'Cause I'm gonna still be stroking.   - Troy, stop!
我也不在意, Rose
I ain't paying him no mind, Rose.
他只是醉了
That ain't nothing but gin talk.
即管吧, Troy! 星期一見
Go on, Troy! I'll see you Monday.
你別來, 朋友
老Don't you come by my house, nigger!
我跟你說過我到時候在做什麼
I done told you what I'm gonna be doing!
星期二才來
Come back on Tuesday!
早安
Good morning.
我可以給你煮早餐, 你要吃嗎?
You ready for breakfast? I can fix you some
在我掛起衣服後
soon as I finish hanging up these clothes.
我喝咖啡就行了
I got the coffee on. That's all right.
來點這個就行了
I just have some of that this morning.
昨天的彩票有結果了
That 651 hit yesterday.
Pearl小姐今個月第二次中了$1
That's the second time this month Miss Pearl hit for a dollar.
看來那些不需要的人總得到更多
Seems like those that need the least always get lucky.
貧窮的人反倒什麼也沒有
Poor folks can't get nothing.
數字又不認人的
Them numbers don't know nobody.
我不知道為你和Lyons都玩這個
I don't know why you fool with 'em, you and Lyons both.
用來消閒
Oh, it's something to do.
你只不過在輸錢而已
You ain't doing nothing but throwing your money away.
Troy, 你知道我能控制自己
Troy, you know I don't play foolishly.
我就這裏五分, 那裏五分的玩
I just play a nickel here and a nickel there.
那你就花了一毛了
That's two nickels you done throwed away.
不全是, 我有時候會贏, 那就扯平了
Nah, I hit sometimes. That makes up for it.
贏了的話, 早晚會用到
Always comes in handy when I do hit.
贏的時候也不聽見你抱怨
I don't hear you complaining then.
我不是在抱怨, 我只是說這很愚蠢
I ain't complaining now. I just say it's foolish,
試著在六百種組合中
trying to guess out of 600 ways
猜出正確號碼
which way the number gonna come.
如果我拿到這些黑人的...
If I had all the money these niggers...
非藉美國人一周放在上面的錢
You negroes throw away on numbers in one week,
只一星期, 我就會很有錢
just one week, I'd be a rich man.
你在這裏說如果和認為是件蠢事
You wishing and calling it foolish
那些人也不會停下不玩
ain't gonna stop folks from playing the numbers.
我肯定
That's one thing for sure.
再者, 玩彩票也有好處的
Besides, some good things come from playing numbers.
看看Pope玩彩票
Look where Pope done bought him
讓他賺了一間餐廳
that restaurant off of numbers.
我不能接受這種人
I can't stand niggers like that.
以前他沒多少錢
Man ain't had two dimes to rub together.
穿著那雙破鞋漫目無的地走
He running around with his shoes all run-over,
到處問人拿香煙
bumming money for cigarettes.
好了, 中獎了
All right. Got lucky there, hit the numbers...
Troy, 我也知道
Troy, I know all about it.
我會說他很有理智
Had good sense. I'll say that for him.
沒把錢花光
Man ain't throw his money away.
我看過有人四天內用掉$2000
I done see niggers go through $2,000 in four days.
他建了間餐廳
Man built him that restaurant down there.
看上去棒極了
Fix it up real nice, too.
然後他不讓有些人進去
Then he won't let nobody come in it.
他們不服務黑人
Negro go in there, can't get no kind of service.
看到有個白人進去點了燉肉湯
Seen a white fella go in there, he orders a bowl of stew.
Pope從大鍋裏為他放了很多肉
Pope pick all the meat out of the pot for him.
那白人的燉肉湯都是肉
Man ain't had nothing but a bowl of meat!
黑人進去點同樣的
Negro go in there behind him,
只會換來馬鈴薯和蘿蔔
he ain't got nothing but the potatoes and the carrots.
還說玩彩票能得到什麼
Talking about what numbers do for people.
你舉了個壞的例子
You picked the wrong example there.
那只讓他成為一個更傻的傻子
Ain't done nothing but made a worser fool out of him
比以前傻得多了
than he already was before.
Troy.
你別再擔心
You ought to stop worrying about
昨天工作時發生的事了
what happened at work yesterday.
我沒在擔心
I ain't worried.
他們只是叫我到理事長的辦公室裏
Just called me down there, the commissioner's office,
所有人都覺得我要被炒了
everybody's worried about them firing me.
我不擔心
I ain't worrying about them firing me.
你也別擔心了
You ain't got to worry about that.
Cory在家嗎?
Where's Cory? Cory in the house?
- Cory!    - 他出去了
- Cory!   - He gone out.
出去了是吧? 他出去
Out, huh? Yeah, he going out
是因為知道我想他築起那藩籬
'cause he know I want him to work on this fence.
我知道他害怕工作
I know how he is. That boy is scared of working.
他這輩子都沒工作過
He ain't done a lick of work in his life.
他要去練習美式足球
He had to go to football practice.
教練想在賽季開始前
Coach wanted them to get in a little extra practice
多加練習
before the season start.
是啊, 我知道他在做怎樣
Oh, yeah, I got his practice all right.
還沒完成家務就出去
Running out of here before he gets his chores done.
Troy, 你怎麼了?
Troy, what is wrong with you this morning?
什麼事不合你意
Don't nothing set right with you.
回去睡足夠才起來
Go on back in there, go to bed, and get up on the other side.
怎麼是我有問題?
Why something got
to be wrong with me?
我沒說我有什麼問題
I ain't said nothing wrong with me.
你對每件事都有意見
Well, you got something to say about everything.
首先是彩票, 然後是那男人
First, it's the numbers, then it's the way the man
如何運作他的餐廳, 然後是Cory的事
run his restaurant, then you done got on Cory.
下一樣會是什麼?
What's it gonna be next?
抬頭看看天氣合不合你意
Take a look up there, see if the weather suit you.
又或者抱怨你要在這
Or is it gonna be how you gonna put up this fence
掛滿衣服的院子裏築起藩籬?
with the clothes hanging in the yard?
你說對了
You hit the nail on the head then.
當然, 我這麼瞭解你
I know you like I know the back of my hand.
進來再喝杯咖啡
Come on in here and get you some more coffee,
看看能不能讓你正常點
see if that don't straighten you up.
因為你今早很不對勁
'Cause you ain't right this morning.
是Troy, 嗨
There's Troy. Hey, Troy.
嗨, Gabe
Hey, Gabe.
- 嗨, Rose   - 嗨, Gabe
- Hey, Rose.   - Hey, Gabe.
你拿著什麼?
What you got there?
你想知道嗎, Rose? 我有水果和蔬菜
You know what I got, Rose? I got fruits and vegetables.
你答應過給我的李子呢?
Where them plums you talking about?
我今天沒有李子, 我剛才正唱著關於那個
I ain't got no plums today. I was just singing that.
我明天會帶來, 我訂了很多李子
I'll have some tomorrow. I put me in a big order for plums.
多到夠分給聖彼得和所有人
I'll have enough plums tomorrow for Saint Peter and everybody!
Troy在生我的氣
Troy mad at me.
Gabe, 我沒有, 為何我要生氣?
I ain't mad at you, Gabe. What I got to be mad at you about?
你又沒對我做什麼
You ain't done nothing to me.
我只是搬到了Pearl小姐那裏
I just move over to Miss Pearl's to keep out from in your way.
我沒什麼打算
I ain't mean no harm by it.
誰說你有?
Who said anything about that?
我可沒有說什麼
I ain't said nothing about that.
你不生我的氣嗎?
You ain't mad at me, is you?
我沒有, 如果我有, 你會知道的
I ain't made at you, Gabe.
If I was mad at you, I'd tell you about it.
進來吧
Come on, get on out of the street. Come on.
我在地下室裏有兩間房, 我擁有自己的門
I got me two rooms in the basement. I got my own door, too.
你想看我的鑰匙嗎?
You want to seemy key?
那是我的鑰匙, 沒有人有同一樣的
That's my own key. Ain't nobody else got a key like that.
那就是我兩間房間的鑰匙
That's my key for my two rooms.
很好, 你有一把屬於你的鑰匙
That's good, Gabe. Got your own key, that's good.
你餓嗎?
You hungry, Gabe?
我剛在給Troy煮早餐
I was just fixing to cook Troy some breakfast.
我吃點餅乾就好了
I'll take some biscuits.
你有餅幹嗎?
Ooh, you got some biscuits?
你知道我在天堂時
Did you know, when I was in heaven,
我和聖彼得每早
every morning, me and Saint Peter
都會坐在門口, 吃點餅幹嗎?
would sit down by the gate and eat some big, fat biscuits?
那時候真棒
Oh, yeah, we had us a good time.
我們就坐著, 然後吃回餅乾
We'd sit there and eat us them biscuits.
然後聖彼得會去睡一會
And then Saint Peter would go off to sleep,
叫我到審判的時候
and tell me to wake him up
叫醒他
when it's time to open the gates for the judgment.
進來吧, 我會一大堆餅乾給你
Well, come on, I'll make you a big batch of biscuits.
Troy, 我看到聖彼得的名冊上有你的名字
Hey, Troy. Saint Peter got your name in his book. I seen it.
寫著Troy Maxson
It say, "Troy Maxson."
我跟他說: 我認識他
I say, "i know him.
我們有同樣的姓 [Maxson]
He got the same name like what I got.
那是我的兄長
"That's my brother."
你要跟我說多少次這故事?
How many times you gonna tell me that, Gabe?
名冊上沒有我的名字, 不會有的
Ain't got my name in the book. Don't have to have my name.
我死過了, 也到過天堂
I done died and went to heaven.
但他有你的名字
But he got your name, though.
一天早上, 聖彼得在看他的名冊
One morning, Saint Peter was looking at his book,
他在準備審判的到來
and he was marking it up for the judgment,
他讓我看了你的名字
and he let me see your name.
在M的那一類別下
He got it in there under "M."
也有Rose的名字
He got Rose's name.
我沒有親眼看到, 但我知道的
I ain't seen it like I seen yours, but I know it's in there.
他有本很大的名冊
He got a great big book! Whoo!
上面有所有存在過的人的名字
He got everybody's name what was ever been born.
他親口告訴我的
That's what he told me.
但我親眼看到你的名字
But I seen your name. I seen it with my own eye.
進去吧
Come in the house.
Rose會煮點什麼給你吃
Rose gonna fix you something to eat now.
我不餓, 我吃了早餐了
I ain't hungry. I done had breakfast
和Jemima姨姨吃
with Aunt Jemima!
她過來, 為我煮了很多烙餅
She come by, cook me up a whole mess of flapjacks!
好了, 進去吧, Rose會...
All right. Come on, let's go in the house. Rose fix us...
還記得我們以前怎麼吃烙餅嗎?
Remember how we used to eat them flapjacks?
記得, 進來吧
Yes, I remember. Come on now.
- 我要走了   - Gabe!
- I got to go!   - Gabe!
- 我要走了   - Gabe, 進來吧
- I got to go!   - Gabe, come on now!
我要去賣李子
I got to go sell my plums!
我賣了點蕃茄
I done sold some tomatoes.
賺了五角, 想看嗎?
Got me two quarters. Want to see?
我要儲起來買個新喇叭
I'm gonna save 'em and buy me a new horn,
好讓到審判時, 聖彼得能聽到
so Saint Peter can hear me when it's time to open the gate.
你聽到嗎?
You hear that?
是地獄之犬
You hear that? That's the hellhound.
我要把它們趕走
I'm gonna chase them out of here.
走啊! 別來這!
Go on! Get out of here! Get out! Get out!
[詩歌]
Gabe在哪?
Where's Gabe?
他又到處跑了
He's gone off somewhere.
他沒有好好吃飯
He ain't eating right.
Pearl小姐說他不肯吃
Miss Pearl say she can't get him to eat nothing.
你想我怎樣?
What you want me to do about it, Rose?
我為他做了我能做的事
I did everything I could for the man.
我不能讓他康復
I can't make him get well.
打仗時他被傷及腦袋了, 你想他怎樣?
Man got half his head blown off, what you expect?
有些事還是能為他做的
Seems like something ought to be done to help him.
他也不打擾誰
The man don't bother nobody.
因為他的腦袋裏有塊金屬碎片
He just mixed up 'cause of that metal plate
所以他才瘋瘋癲癲, 沒理由...
he got in his head. Ain't no sense in...
謝謝, 沒理由讓他住在醫院
Thank you. Ain't no sense in sending him to the hospital.
至少他會吃點什麼
At least he'd be eating right.
他們會照顧他
They could help him take care of himself.
沒有人想被鎖起來
Don't nobody want to be locked up, Rose.
你為何想鎖起他?
What you want to lock the man up for?
他上戰場
Man going down there,
跟日本人打仗
over there and fight that war, messing with them japs,
炸傷了腦袋
getting half his head blown off.
他們隨便賠了三千塊, 我都接受了
They give him a lousy $3,000. I got to swoop down on that.
你又要說這個了嗎?
Is you fixing to get into that again?
他的腦袋裏有塊金屬碎片
He got a metal plate in his head.
而那就是我得到這間房子的原因
That's the only reason I got a roof over my head
就因為那金屬碎片
is 'cause of that metal plate.
你沒理由自責的
Ain't no sense in you blaming yourself for nothing.
他不能管理好那筆錢
Gabe was in no condition to manage that money.
你為他做了正確的事
You done what was right by him.
沒人能說你不是
Can't nobody say you ain't done what was right by him.
看看你照顧他多久了
Look how long you took care of him.
一直至到他想要有自己的地方, 才搬去Pearl小姐那
Till he wanted his own place
and moved over there with Miss Pearl.
女人, 那不是我想說的, 我只是...
That ain't what I'm saying, woman. I'm just...
我只是在說事實
I'm just stating the facts.
要是我的弟弟沒有受傷
If my brother didn't have a metal plate in his head,
我就不會有上廁所的地方
I wouldn't have a pot to piss in
不會有個後院
or a window to throw it out of.
我都53歲了...
And I'm 53...
你要去哪?
Where you going off to?
你近期每個星期六都出去
You been running out of here every Saturday for weeks.
我以為你會築起那藩籬
I thought you were gonna work on this fence.
我去Taylor的酒吧裏
I'm gonna go down to Taylors' and, uh...
媽媽?
Mama?
Cory, 你爸爸對你今早還沒完成家務
Oh, Cory. Your daddy like to have a fit with you
就跑出去非常憤怒
running out of here this morning without doing your chores.
你還好嗎?
You all right?
他說你本該幫忙築起藩籬
He say you supposed to be helping him with the fence.
我說過要去練習啊
I told you I had to go to practice.
他過去幾個星期六都這樣說
And he's been saying that the last four or five Saturdays,
然後就跑到Taylor的酒吧
and then don't ever do nothing but go down to Taylors'.
你有跟他說錄取的事嗎?
You told him about the recruiter?
有
Yeah, I told him.
- 那他怎麼說? - 他沒說什麼
- Well, what'd he say? - He didn't say nothing too much.
在他回來前快完成家務
Go on and get started on your chores before he gets back here.
在他回來又要抱怨前
Go on and scrub down them steps
快去刷刷地板
before he come back here hollering and carrying on!
現在啊, 小子
Go! Boy, go!
繼續吧, Troy, 你早晚會把我嚇死的
Go on, Troy. You liked to scare me to death.
比賽怎麼了?
What was the score of the game?
Lucille在電話說過, 但我沒留意
Lucille had me on the phone. I couldn't keep up with it.
我為何在意比賽了? 來吧, 女人
What do I care about the game? Come here, woman.
我以為你去Taylor那裏
I thought you went down to Taylors'
就是為了看比賽, 讓我走
to listen to the game. Go on, Troy.
我以為你要築起那藩籬
I thought you're supposed to be putting up the fence.
我會去的, 在我處理好...
I'll put it up when I finish with what...
我手上的事
Is at hand.
快去吧, 真不懂你的
Go on, Troy. I ain't studying you!
但我懂你, 我會好好的弄清楚你
I'm studying you. I'm finna do my homework.
夠了
Troy, you better leave me alone!
Cory回來了嗎?
Where Cory? That boy brought his butt home yet?
他在上面做家務
He's upstairs doing his chores.
Cory, 快下來...
Cory, get your butt...
- 你去哪?   - 很快會來
- Where you going?   - I'll be right back.
- 何時?   - 就街口那
- When?   - I'm just going right down the street.
去哪? 跟誰?
Where? Who?
Troy, 進去吧
Troy, go in the house.
你到現在才回來嗎?
You just now coming here from leaving this morning?
- 對, 我要去練習   - 對什麼?
- Yeah, I had to go to football practice... - Yeah, what?
對, 先生
Yes, sir.
我才不看你一會
I ain't but two seconds off you, no way.
那垃圾箱都要滿了
That garbage sitting in there, overflowing.
你沒做過家務
You ain't done none of your chores.
現在也沒禮貌
Now you come in here, talking about, "yeah."
我剛想做, 爸
I was just getting ready to do my chores now, pop.
你的首要是星期六幫我築起藩籬
Your first chore is to help me with this fence on Saturday.
所有事都放在那之後
Everything else come after that.
去拿木鋸, 我們要鋸開這些木板
Now, get that saw, we gonna cut these boards.
嘿, 爸
Hey, pop.
你為何不買電視?
Why don't you buy a TV?
我要來做什麼?
What I want with a TV? What I want one of them for?
現在每人家裏都有一台
Everybody got one. Earl, Ba Bra, Jesse.
我不是在問誰有電視, 我是問要來做什麼?
I ain't asked who had one, I said what I want with one?
所以你可以看啊, 現在有很多不同的節目
So, you can watch it. They got lots of things on TV.
- 棒球也有   - 是嗎?
- Baseball and everything.   - Yeah?
我們可以看世界大賽
We could watch the world series.
- 那買電視要多少錢?    - 我不清楚
- Yeah, how much this TV cost?   - I don't know.
我看見過優惠價二百塊
They got 'em on sale for about $200.
- 二百塊?   - 那不算貴, 爸
- $200?   - That ain't that much, pop.
是啊, 才二百塊而已
No, that's just $200.
你有留意那屋頂嗎?
You see that roof you got sitting over your head at night?
我來告訴你那屋頂的事
Let me tell you something about that roof.
那屋頂已經十年沒塗上焦油了
It's been 10 years since that roof was last tarred.
然後到了冬天下雪時
See, now snow come this winter,
雪積聚在屋頂上
sit up on that roof like it is,
然後一點點的慢慢地滲透到裏面
it's gonna seep inside, just gonna be a little bit,
你甚至不會注意到
you ain't gonna hardly notice it,
然後當你發現時
then next thing you know,
早已滲透到各處
it's gonna be leaking all over the house.
然後因為積水, 木材會腐蝕
Then the wood rot from all that water,
到時候你就需要把整個屋頂換掉
and you gonna need a whole new roof.
你猜要多少才能修好?
Now how much you think it cost to get that roof fixed?
- 我不知道   - $264現金, 明白了嗎?
- I don't know.   - $264 cash money. See?
當你在想買電視
While you be thinking about a TV,
我就得擔心頭上的屋頂
I got to be thinking about the roof
又或是要修理的東西
or whatever else go wrong around here.
如果你有二百塊, 你會怎做?
Now if you had $200, what would you do?
修理屋頂還是買電視?
Fix the roof, or buy a TV?
買電視, 當屋頂開始滲水時
I'd buy a TV. And when the roof started to leak,
我才修理它
if it needed fixing, I'd fix it.
你哪來的錢?
Where you gonna get your money from?
你都花在買電視上了
You done spent it on a TV.
到時候你在裏面
You gonna sit up in there,
看著漏水滴到你的新電視上嗎?
let that water run all over your brand-new TV?
爸, 我知道你有錢的
Pop, you got the money. I know you do.
- 在哪?    - 銀行裏
- Where I got it at, huh?   - In the bank.
你想看我的存摺嗎?
You want to see my bank book?
你想看我那$73.22的存款嗎?
You want to see that $73.22 I got sitting up in there?
你不需要一次付清
You don't have to pay for it all at one time.
可以先給首期, 之後分期付款
You can put a down payment on it, and carry it on with you.
除非情況緊急, 我才不會讓自己欠別人東西
Not me. I ain't owing nobody nothing if I can help it.
遲了付款, 他們就會來帶走它
Miss a payment, they come and snatch it right out of your house.
那你就白付了, 明白了嗎?
Then what you got, huh? See?
如果我有整整$200塊, 我會選擇買電視
Now, when I get $200 clear, I'll buy me a TV.
要是我手上有$264塊, 我就會選擇修理屋頂
Right now, when I get $264, I'm gonna get that roof fixed.
爸...
Oh, pop...
如果你想買電視
You go get you $200
就自己賺$200塊
and buy you a TV if you want to.
我的錢要花在更實用的地方
I got better things to do with my money.
我賺不到$200, 我甚至沒見過$200
I can't get $200. I ain't never seen $200.
好吧, 我跟你說
All right, I'll tell you what.
我們各人付$100
You get $100, I'll put the other $100 with it.
好吧, 等著我
All right, I'm gonna show you.
現在給我看你如何切開這些木板
Yeah, show me how you can cut these boards right now.
拿著, 那值$200塊
There you go. That's $200 worth.
- 匹茲堡海盜隊今天贏了   - 是嗎?
- The Pirates won today.   - Yeah?
連續贏五場了
That makes five in a row.
我沒在意海盜隊, 他們都只有白人球員
I ain't thinking about no Pirates. They got an all-white team.
他們有個波多黎各的球員, Clemente是吧?
Got that boy, though, that Puerto Rican boy, Clemente?
也不讓他出出場
Don't even half play him.
如果給那孩子機會, 他會是位偉大的球員
That boy could be something if they'd give him a chance.
讓他上一天場, 隔天又坐板凳了
Play him one day, sit him on the bench the next.
他也常上場啊
He gets lots of chances to play.
我在說每天都上場, 當正選
I'm talking about playing every day, playing regular,
這才能學到更多啊
so you can get your timing, that's what I'm talking about.
他們隊裏也有些白人不是每天都能上場
They got some white guys on the team that don't play every day.
你總不能讓全部人上場
You can't play everybody at the same time.
如果有個白人球員是當後備的
If they got a white fellow sitting on the bench,
你可以肯定他根本不會打棒球
you can bet your last dollar he can't play.
有色人種要出色兩倍才能當正選
Colored guy got to be twice as good to get on the team.
那就是我不想你進球隊的原因
That's why I don't want you getting all tied up in them sports.
進去了又如何?
Man on the team, what it get him?
球隊的有色人種不被重用
Got colored on the team, don't even use him.
如同沒有他們一樣, 所有球隊都是這樣的
Same as not having them. All them teams the same.
亞特蘭大勇士隊也有Hank Aaron和Wes Covington
The Braves got Hank Aaron and Wes Covington.
Hank Aaron已經有43個全壘打了, 算上今天兩個的話
Hank Aaron hit two home runs today. That makes 43.
Aaron不算什麼, 那是你該做的
Aaron ain't nobody. That's what you supposed to do.
你該全力以赴
That's how the game's supposed to be played.
沒別的, 不過是
Ain't nothing to it. It's a matter of getting
抓準時機然後揮棒
your timing and follow through.
我現在也可以打43個全壘打
Hell, I can hit 43 home runs right now.
你不能在美國職業棒球大聯盟裏打得出來
Not off no Major-League pitcher, you couldn't.
我們在黑人聯盟裏有更強的投手
We had better pitching in the negro leagues.
我在Satchel Paige身上打過七次全壘打
I hit seven home runs off of Satchel Paige.
你不會找到比他更好的球員
You can't get no better than that.
Sandy Koufax, 他是聯盟裏三振次數最多的
Sandy Koufax, he leading the league in strikeouts.
我不是在想Sandy Koufax的事
I ain't thinking about no Sandy Koufax.
還有Warren Spahn和Lew Burdette, 我猜你...
You got Warren Spahn and Lew Burdette. I bet you...
我不想再說了
I'm through with it now.
去鋸木板吧
Go and cut them boards.
你媽媽跟我說你被大學美式足球隊錄取了
Your mama told me you got recruited by a college football team.
真有此事嗎?
Is that right?
對, Zellman教練說
Yeah, coach Zellman say
晚點會有負責人跟你商討
the recruiter gonna be coming by to talk to you.
讓你簽同意書
Get you to sign the permission papers.
我以為你會在A&P裏工作
I thought you was supposed to be working down the A&P.
你放學後不是應該到那裏工作嗎?
Ain't you supposed to be working down there after school?
Stawicki先生說他會替我留著位子
Mr. Stawicki say he gonna hold my job for me
直到賽季結束
until after the football season.
他說下周起, 我可以只上週末的班
He said starting next week, I can work weekends.
小子, 我以為我們說好了
Boy, I thought we had an understanding about this football stuff.
你應該繼續完成家務
You supposed to keep up with your chores,
繼續在A&P工作
hold your job down there at the A&P.
你今天大半天不在
You ain't been around here all day on a Saturday,
也沒完成家務
ain't none of your chores done.
現在你說你辭職了?
Now you come telling me you done quit your job?
- 我週末也會上班啊   - 當然了
- I'm gonna be working weekends. - You damn right you are!
那負責人也不必到來
And ain't no need for nobody to be coming around here,
跟我說籤署的事
talking to me about signing nothing.
爸, 你不能這樣做
Pop, you can't do that.
他大老遠從北卡羅萊納州來
He's coming all the way from north Carolina.
我才不在乎
I don't care where he coming from!
聽著, 小子
Look, boy,
那些白人無論如何也不會讓你
the white man ain't gonna let you
碰美式足球的
get nowhere with no football no way.
你繼續你的學業, 所以你可以...
Now you get your book-learning, so you can, uh,
在A&P有進升的機會, 還有學習維修車子
work your way up at the A&P
and learn how to fix cars,
或者建築, 讓自己有一技傍身
or build houses, get you a trade.
那樣你才有競爭力
This way, you got something can't nobody take away from you.
你的雙手
You go in and learn how to put your hands to good use
該做比清理垃圾更好的工作
besides hauling other people's garbage.
我的成績很好, 爸
I get good grades, pop.
那就是他們會跟你商討的原因
That's why the recruiter want to talk with you.
你的成績也要好才能被錄取的
You got to keep up your grades to get recruited.
這樣我就有機會上大學
This way, I'll be going to college, I'll get a chance.
首先, 你去A&P那拿回你的工作
First, you get your butt down there and get your job back.
Stawicki先生已經聘請了其他人
Mr. Stawicki done already hired somebody else
因為我跟他說我要打美式足球
'cause I told him I was playing football.
我比我想像中還蠢
You a bigger fool than I thought.
你竟然讓別人代替了你的位置
You gonna let somebody take away your job,
好讓你能打什麼美式足球
so you can play some football.
你上哪賺錢
Where you gonna get your money
照顧你的女友什麼的?
to take care of your girlfriend and whatnot?
到底有多蠢
What kind of foolishness is that
才會讓別人代替了自己?
to let somebody take away your job?
我週末還是會去工作的
I'm still gonna be working weekends.
不, 你去找另一份工作
No. You getting out of here and finding you another job.
別這樣, 爸, 我還得練習呢
Come on, pop. I gotta practice.
我不能同時工作和練習
I can't work after school and play football, too.
Zellman教練說球隊需要我
The team needs me, that's what Coach Zellman say.
我才不介意他說什麼, 我說了算, 明白了嗎?
I don't care what nobody say. I'm the boss. You understand?
我是你的父親, 我說的才算
I'm the boss around here. I do the only saying what counts.
- 別這樣...    - 我問你: 你明白了嗎?
- Come on...  - I asked you, "do you understand?"
- 明白   - 什麼?
- Yeah.   - What?
- 明白, 先生    - 好了
- Yes, sir.   - All right.
你去A&P看看能不能取回你的工作
You get on down there to that A&P and see if you can get your job back.
如果只能二選其一, 那就放棄進球隊吧
If you can't do both, then you quit the football team.
人生不如意事十常八九
You got to take the crookeds with the straights.
明白, 先生
Yes, sir.
我可以問你點事嗎?
Can I ask you a question?
你又要問什麼?
What the hell you got to ask me?
你該問Stawicki先生工作的事
Mr. Stawicki the one you got the questions for.
你為何從不喜歡我?
How come you ain't never liked me?
喜歡你? 誰說我一定要喜歡你?
Like you? Who the hell said I got to like you?
有什麼規定要我一定要喜歡你?
What law is there say I got to like you?
既然站在我面前
You want to stand up in front of my face
問這蠢極了的問題
and ask a damn fool-ass question like that.
還扯什麼喜歡誰
Talk about liking somebody.
說話時站近點, 小子
Come here, boy, when I talk to you.
該死的, 站好, 我問你
Straighten up, god damn it! I asked you a question.
- 有什麼規定要我一定要喜歡你?   - 沒有
- What law is there say I got to like you?   - None.
正是, 你三餐溫飽嗎?
All right, then. Don't you eat every day?
我問你問題時, 你就得回答我
Answer me when I talk to you.
- 你三餐溫飽嗎?   - 對
- Don't you eat every day?   - Yeah.
小子, 你一天在我的地方
Nigger, as long as you in my house,
你就得加在句子最後加上"先生"
you put a "Sir" on the end of it when you talk to me.
- 是, 先生   - 你每天都有飯吃?
- Yes, sir.   - You eat every day?
- 是, 先生    - 有地方住?
- Yes, sir.   - Got a roof over your head?
- 是, 先生   - 有衣服穿?
- Yes, sir.   - Got clothes on your back?
- 是, 先生   - 原因呢?
- Yes, sir.   - Why you think that is?
- 全因為你   - 我當然知道是因為我
- 'Cause of you.   - Hell, I know it's 'cause of me.
但你認為是因為什麼?
But why do you think that is?
因為你喜歡我?
'Cause you like me?
"喜歡"你
"Like" you.
我每天一大清早出去工作
I go out of here every morning,
還得時時刻刻忍受那些白人 [crackers帶侮辱之意]
I bust my butt putting up with them crackers every day
才算得上"喜歡"你
'cause I "like" you.
你簡直是我見過最愚蠢的人, 那是我的職責
You about the biggest fool I ever saw. It's my job.
我的責任
It's my responsibility.
一個男人就該照顧他的家庭
A man is supposed to take care of his family.
你住在我的房子裏, 吃我買回來的食物
You live in my house, fill your belly with my food,
我照顧你是因為你是我的兒子啊
put your behind on my bed because you're my son.
而不是我喜歡你, 照顧你是我的職責
Not 'cause I like you. 'Cause it's my duty to take care of you.
我得承擔起這個責任
I owe a responsibility to you.
現在我就說清楚
Now, let's get this straight right here and now,
以免你將來又說同樣的話
before it go along any further.
我不需要喜歡你
I ain't got to like you.
Rand先生每星期發薪給我不是因為他喜歡我
Mr. Rand don't give me my money come payday 'cause he like me.
是因為他欠我的
He give it to me 'cause he owe me.
現在我已給了所有我該給你的
Now I done give you everything I got to give you.
我把你帶到這個世界上啊!
I give you your life!
你媽媽和我都商討好各自的職責
Me and your mama worked that out between us,
而喜歡你不是我的工作之一
and liking your black ass wasn't part of the bargain.
你從今起別再
Now don't you go through life
擔心別人是否喜歡你
worrying about whether somebody like you, or not.
你該想他們沒有負了你
You best be making sure they're doing right by you.
- 明白了嗎?   - 明白, 先生
- You understand what I'm saying?   - Yes, sir.
那現在滾開, 去A&P拿回你的工作
Then get the hell out of my face and get on down to that A&P!
你為何就不讓那孩子打美式足球呢, Troy?
Why don't you go ahead and let the boy play football, Troy?
他只想像你一樣在運動有點成就
He just want to be like you with the sports.
我不想他重蹈覆轍
I don't want him to be like me.
我想他走條和我完全不同的路
I want him to get as far away from my life
越不同越好
as he possibly can get.
你是我生命中唯一遇過的好事, Rose
You the only decent thing ever happened to me, Rose.
我希望他找個像你一樣好的女人
And I wish him that.
除此之外我不希望他像我一樣
But I don't wish him nothing else from my life.
我在他出生的那天就決定
I decided 17 years ago,
那孩子不要參與什麼運動
that boy wasn't gonna get involved in no sports.
在我明白運動裏的不公之後
Not after what they did to me in the sports.
你為何就不承認你當時不能進職業聯盟是因為年紀?
Why don't you just admit you were too old for the Major Leagues?
就承認一次?
For once, why don't you just admit that?
別跟我來年紀這套
Don't you come tellin' me I was too old.
是因為我是有色人種而已, 我現在都53歲了
I just wasn't the right color. Hell, I'm 53 years old,
但我肯定我能打出比S的.269更好的成績
I can do better than Selkirk's .269 right now.
過了40歲還怎樣打棒球?
How were you gonna play ball when you were over 40?
有時候你說的話真不合邏輯
Sometimes, I can't get no sense out of you.
我很清醒, 女人
I got good sense, woman.
我清楚知道別讓運動傷了他的身心
I got sense enough not to let that boy get hurt playing no sports.
你太疼愛他了
You mothering the boy too much.
讓他老是擔心別人是否喜歡自己
Worrying about whether people "like" him or not.
那孩子做的所有事, 都是為了給你看
Everything that boy do, he do for you.
他想你稱讚他, 僅此而已
He wants you to say, "good job, son." That's all.
Rose, 我沒時間做這些事, 他好好的活著
I ain't got time for that, Rose. He's alive, he's healthy.
就得自己找出路, 我也得繼續自己的生活
He's got to make his own way. I made mine.
他將來出社會後
Ain't nobody gonna hold his hand
沒有人會時常照顧他的
when he get out there in the world.
Troy, 時代不同了
Times have changed, Troy.
人會變的
People change.
世界在變, 而你根本不知道
The world changing, and you can't even see it.
女人, 我盡我所能地工作
Woman, I do the best I can do.
每星期五我帶著
I come in here every Friday,
一袋馬鈴薯和一桶豬油回來
I carry a sack of potatoes and a bucket of lard.
你們才得以不用工作
You all line up at the door with your hands out.
我連最後的錢都用在你們身上
I give you the lint from my pockets.
我付出了我的血汗
I give you my sweat and my blood.
我無法給你們同情, 早已用光了
I ain't got no tears. I done spent them.
我們晚上到樓上做愛
We go upstairs in that room at night, I fall down on you
在你裏面給了我唯一所剩的
and try to blast a hole into forever.
星期一早上起來, 帶著桌上煮好的午餐
I get up Monday morning, find my lunch on the table,
出去繼續我的生活
go out and make my way.
試著捱到星期五
Find my strength to get me through to next Friday.
那就是我能給的, Rose
That's all I got, Rose.
那已經是我能給你們的全部了
That's all I got to give.
已經沒什麼可以再給你們了!
Can't give nothing else!
Maxson先生?
Mr. Maxson?
理事長想見你
Commissioner will see you now.
Rose!
嘿, Ro!
Hey, Ro!
我真想看到Rand先生當時的糗樣
I wish I could've seen Mr. Rand's face when he told you.
他聽了判決後都說不出話來了
He couldn't get it out his mouth. Liked to bit his tongue.
當他們叫我到理事長的辦公室時
When they called me down there to the commissioner's office,
Rand像所有人一樣都以為他們要炒了我
he thought they was gonna fire me, like everybody else.
我可沒有這樣想
Oh, I didn't think they was gonna fire you.
我以為他們要給你警告信
I thought they's gonna put you on the warning paper.
嘿, Rose! 對, Rand先生這下一定無話可說了
Hey, Rose! Yeah, Mr. Rand liked to bit his tongue.
我看到你跑到Taylor的酒吧
I see you run right down there to Taylors'
告訴那個叫Alberta的女子
and told that Alberta gal.
嘿, Rose! 我跟所有人都會說的, 嘿, Ro!
Hey, Rose! I told everybody. Hey, Ro!
我去那兌現支票 [花錢]
I went down there to cash my check.
嘿!
Hey!
別叫了, 我知道你回來了
Hush all that hollering. I know you out here.
理事長怎說了?
What they say down at the commissioner's office?
我叫你的時候你就該立刻回應我, 女人
You supposed to come when I call you, woman.
Bono也懂
Bono will tell you that.
你叫Lucille時她不也立刻回應嗎?
Don't Lucille come when you call her?
閉嘴吧老兄, 我又不是狗
Man, hush your mouth. I ain't no dog.
說什麼立刻回應你
Talk about come when you call me.
Bono, 看到了嗎? 我以前有隻狗
You hear this, Bono? I used to have me an old dog
也像這樣自以為高人一等
get uppity like that.
你喊他來, 他也不理會
You say, "come here, Blue,"he just lay there, look at you.
最後通常都是被追著打, 為了教訓他
End up getting a stick chasin' him away, trying to make him come.
我不在意你和你的狗
I ain't studying you and your dog.
我記得你總會唱起歌來
I remember you used to sing that old song.
沒有人想聽啊
Nobody wants to hear that old song.
他唱起來時, 總讓Cory到處跑
Used to have Cory runnin' around here singin' that song.
我也記得那首歌
Hell, I remember that song myself.
那是我爸爸的歌
That's my daddy's song.
他創作的
My daddy made up that song.
我才不在乎誰作的, 沒有人想聽你唱的
I don't care who made it up. Don't nobody want to hear you sing it.
你這麼興奮回來, 我就猜到他們沒有炒了你
You come in here carrying on, I reckon they ain't fired you.
理事長到底說了什麼?
What they say down there at
the commissioner's office?
Rose, 聽著, Rand先生在理事長會見我後
Look here, Rose. Mr. Rand called me in his office
叫我到他的辦公室
after I got back from talkin' to them people down there.
他叫我進去並說
He called me in his office and told me...
他們要讓我當司機!
They was making me a driver!
- Troy, 你在說笑吧!   - 不信問Bono
- Troy, you kidding!   - No, I ain't. Ask Bono.
那真好, Troy
That's great, Troy.
那你再不用跟那些人糾纏了
Now you don't have to hassle them people no more.
天啊, 沒想到今天你會來
Oh, hell. I didn't think I was gonna see you today.
我以為你在監獄裏
I thought you was in jail.
聽到消息說他們掃蕩Seefus的店
Got it all over the courier about them raiding Seefus' place
那個你跟那些不倫不類的傢伙經常去的地方
where you be hanging out with all them thugs.
嘿, 爸, 那跟我沒關係
Hey, pop, that ain't got nothing to do with me.
我沒在那賭博
I don't go down there gambling.
我只是去那跟樂隊交流
I just go down there to sit in with the band.
那賭博跟我沾不上關係
I ain't got nothing to do with the gambling part.
他們那裏有些很好的音樂人
They got some good music down there.
那裏只有流氓而已
They got some rogues is what they got.
Bono先生你還好嗎? 你好, Rose
How you been, Mr. Bono? Hi, Rose.
我知道你今晚在Crawford Grill有演出 [爵士樂俱樂部]
I see where you playing down at the Crawford Grill tonight.
你怎麼又不帶Bonnie來?
How come you ain't brought Bonnie like I told you?
你該帶上她來
You shoulda brought Bonnie.
她很久沒來過了
She ain't been by in a month of Sundays.
我剛巧路過而已
I was just in the neighborhood.
- 想著見你們一面   - 又來了
- Thought I'd stop by.   - Here it comes.
你爸爸升職了
Your daddy got a promotion on the rubbish.
他是第一個駕駛垃圾車的有色人種
He gonna be the first colored driver.
什麼也不用做
Ain't got to do nothin' but sit up there
像白人一樣坐著看報紙就行了
and read the paper, like them white fellas.
爸, 如果你識字的話, 那會是件好事
Hey, pop, if you knew how to read, you'd be all right.
不不, 你指如果這老兄懂得駕駛的話
Nah, nah. You mean if the nigger knew how to drive,
那才是件好事
he'd be all right.
一直跟那些人爭論駕車的問題
Been fighting with them people about driving
然而連駕照也沒有
and ain't even got a license.
Rand先生知道你沒有駕照的吧?
Mr. Rand know you ain't got no driver's license?
駕車很容易
Driving ain't nothing.
就是扭軑盤而已
All you do is point the truck where you want it to go.
並不難
Driving ain't nothing.
他們知道你沒有駕照嗎?
Do they know you ain't got no driver's license?
那才是我問的
That's what I'm talkin' about.
我不是問你駕駛是否容易
I ain't asked if driving was easy.
我問你Rand先生是否知道你沒有駕照一事
I asked if Mr. Rand know you ain't got no driver's license.
那人沒必要知道我的事
The man ain't got to know my business.
待他發現時我已經有兩三個駕照了
Time he find out, I have two or three of them driver's license.
- 聽著, 爸   - 我就知道你會這麼說
- Say, look here, pop.   - I knew it was coming.
我知道你要說什麼
I knew what kinda "look here, pop" that was.
那小子又要問我拿錢了
Nigger finna ask me for some money.
今天是星期五, 又是我的發薪日
It's Friday night, it's my payday.
那些沒被拘捕的流氓會在Avenue大道流連
All them rogues down on the Avenue, the ones that ain't in jail,
Lyons趕著去跟他們會合
and Lyons is hopping in his shoes to get down there with them.
聽著, 爸
Now, see, pop,
如果你讓別人說完他要說的
if you gave somebody else a chance to talk sometime,
你就會知道我要還你答應過的十塊
you'd see I was fixing to pay you back your $10 like I told you.
拿著, 我說過待Bonnie發薪了我會還你的
Here. I told you I'd pay you when Bonnie got paid.
不, 你自己留著那十塊, 存到銀行裏
No, you keep that $10. Put it in the bank.
下次你覺得又要來這裏向我拿錢時
Next time you feel like you wanna come by here
你就從銀行拿出這十塊
and ask me for somethin', you go down there and get that.
拿著屬於你的十塊吧, 爸
Here you go your $10, pop.
我說過我不想你給我
I told you, I don't want you to give me nothing.
我只想借而已
I just wanted to borrow $10.
不, 你留著下次用
No, you keep that for the next time you want to ask me.
別這樣, 爸, 拿著吧
Come on, pop, here go your $10.
Troy, 你為何不讓那孩子還錢?
Troy, why don't you let the boy pay you back?
你替他拿吧, Rose, 如果你不拿
Here you go, Rose. If you don't take it,
接下來六個月他又要不斷嘮叨此事了
I'm gonna hear about it for the next six months.
你也可以順道給出你的那份薪金, Troy
You can hand yours over, too, Troy.
Bono, 你看到他們怎對待我了嗎
You see this, Bono? You see how they do me?
看到, Lucille也是這樣做
Yeah, Lucille do me the same way.
嘿, 是Troy的兒子啊
Hey. Hey, there's Troy's boy!
Gabe叔叔, 你最近好嗎?
How you doing, Uncle Gabe?
Lyons!
萬獸之王
The king of the jungle!
嘿, Rose, 我有朵玫瑰花給你
Rose. Hey, Rose, I got a flower for you.
我親自摘的, 就跟你名字一樣的玫瑰
I picked it myself. That's the same rose like you is.
你真有心, Gabe
Aw, that's right nice of you, Gabe.
Gabe叔叔, 你最近在做什麼?
What you been doing, Uncle Gabe?
噢, 我一直在追趕地獄之犬
Oh, I been chasing hellhounds and waiting for the time
並等著告訴聖彼得打開天堂的門
to tell Saint Peter to open the gates.
你在追趕地獄之犬?
You been chasing hellhounds, huh?
你做得很正確
Well, you doing the right thing, Uncle Gabe.
- 總有人要去趕走他們   - 是的, 我也知道
- Somebody's got to chase 'em.   - Oh, yeah, I know it.
魔鬼很強大, 不是那麼容易打敗
The devil's strong. The devil ain't no pushover.
地獄之犬一直在尋找人類的氣息 [應為sniff, 非snip]
Hellhounds snipping at everybody's heels.
但我已經準備好喇叭, 等待審判日的來臨
But I got my trumpet waiting on the judgment time.
為了哈米吉多頓之戰作準備嗎? [聖經中世界末日最後一戰]
Waiting on the Battle of Armageddon, huh?
噢, 那眨眼就會結束
Oh, ain't gonna be too much of a battle
當上帝揮動審判之劍時
when god get to waving that judgment sword.
如果天堂的門關上的話, 那時候人們就得費時
But the people's gonna have a hell of a time
等待進入天堂了
trying to get into heaven if them gates ain't open.
你聽到這嗎, 爸?
You hear this, pop?
Gabe叔叔, 你人真好
Uncle Gabe, you all right.
Lyons.
萬獸之王
The king of the jungle!
Gabe, 你留下來吃晚餐嗎?
You stayin' for supper, Gabe?
你要我煮你的份嗎?
You want me to fix you a plate?
我要份三明治就好了, 不用煮我的份
I'll just take a sandwich, Rose. I don't want no plate.
我喜歡用雙手拿著來吃, 三明治好了
I want to eat with my hands. I'll take a sandwich.
你呢Lyons? 留下嗎? 在煮牛小排呢
What about you, Lyons? You stayin'? Got some short ribs cooking.
不了, 我通常在演出完結後才用餐的
Nah. I won't eat nothing till after we finish playing.
你應該來看看我演出, 爸
You ought to come down, listen to me play, pop.
噢, 我不喜歡那些像中國音樂一樣的嘈音
Oh, I don't like all that Chinese music, all that noise.
去洗手吧, Gabe, 我現在弄三明治
Go in there and wash up, Gabe. I'll fix you a sandwich.
Troy在生我的氣
Troy mad at me.
你為何生他的氣?
What you mad at Uncle Gabe for?
他以為Troy為了
He think Troy mad at him
他搬到Pearl那裏而生氣
'cause he moved over there to Miss Pearl's.
我才沒有生氣, 他可以住他想住的地方
I ain't mad at the man. He can live where he want to live at.
他為何搬到那裏? Pearl小姐任何人都不喜歡
Well, what he move over there for? Miss Pearl don't like nobody.
噢, 她不介意他在, 還對他頗好
Oh, she don't mind him none. She treat him real nice.
她就不允許他唱歌而已
She just don't allow all that singing.
她不介意他在為她付租金, 僅此而已
She don't mind that rent he be paying. That's what she don't mind.
Troy, 我不想再跟你討論此事
Troy, I ain't goin' through that with you no more.
他搬到那因為他想要有自己的地方
He moved over there 'cause he wanted his own place.
他可以隨他所想的做
He can come and go as he please.
他可以在這裏做他想做的, 我也不介意
He can come and go as he please here. I wasn't stoppin' him.
我也沒規定他什麼
I wasn't putting no rules on the man.
你明知道那是兩碼子的事
That ain't the same thing, and you know it.
我不想再討論這話題
Now that's the last I wanna hear about that.
我不想再聽到Gabe和Miss Pearl之間的事
I don't wanna hear nothin' else about Gabe and Miss Pearl.
還有下周...
And next week...
我準備好了, Rose
I'm ready for my sandwich, Rose.
還有下周, 當從學校來的負責人到來
And next week, when that recruiter come from that school,
我要你簽署讓Cory進美式足球隊
I want you to sign that paper and go on and let Cory play football.
我不想再聽你說起此事
That'll be the last I have to hear about that.
Cory被錄取了? 他要到哪所學校?
Cory got recruited? What school he goin' to?
我不想再理會Cory的事
I ain't thinking about Cory nothing.
那小子把這裏當成他的地方
Boy walking around here smelling his piss,
以為可以為所欲為
thinking he gonna do what he want to do,
不聽我的說話
irregardless of what I say.
Bono, 聽著, 我離開理事長的辦公室後
Look here, Bono, I left the commissioner's office
去了A&P那裏
and went down to the A&P.
那小子根本沒在那工作, 他跟我說謊了
That boy ain't workin' down there, he lied to me.
說他取回了工作, 週末得上班什麼的
Tellin' me he got his job back, tellin' me he workin' weekend,
說他課後在上班
tellin' me he workin' after school.
Stawicki說他根本沒來上班
Mr. Stawicki says he ain't working down there at all.
Cory只是長大了而已
Cory just growing up.
他有了自己的想法, 不能再聽你說的
He just bustin' at the seams, tryin' to fill out your shoes.
我才不在意他想什麼
I don't care what he doing.
當他到了反叛期
When he get to the place where he want to disobey me,
那就是出外打拼的時候了, Bono也懂
then it's time for him to move on. Bono will tell you that.
我肯定他不能違抗他父親後
I bet he ain't never disobeyed his daddy
不用受罰
without paying the consequences.
我根本沒機會違抗他
I ain't never had the chance.
我父親到處走, 我根本沒看過他
My daddy came on through, but I ain't never knew him to see him.
或者他在想什麼, 去哪了
Or what he had on his mind, or where he went.
就四海為家, 尋找新大陸
Just moving on through. Searching out the new land.
那就是以前的人用的
That's what the old folks used to call it.
一個人要是到處搬, 不停換女人
See a fella moving around from place to place, woman to woman,
他們叫這"尋找新大陸"
they call it "searching out the new land."
我也不清楚他有沒有找到
I can't say if he ever found it.
我來到這地方, 也不想有孩子
I come along, didn't want no kids.
我也不知道我能否安定下來
I didn't know if I was gonna be in one place long enough
當個爸爸
to fix on 'em right as their daddy.
我想不如還是尋找新大陸算了
I figured I was going searching, too.
沒想過我跟Lucille在一起的時間
As it turn out, I been hooked up with Lucille
也幾乎有你爸爸和Rose在一起那麼久了
for near about as long as your daddy been with Rose.
已經16年了
Going on 16 years.
有時候我真希望自己不認識我的父親
Sometimes, I wish I'd never known my daddy.
他不在意孩子過得怎樣, 對他來說毫不重要
He ain't cared nothing about no kids. A kid to him wasn't nothing.
他只想你快點成人
All he wanted you to do was learn how to walk,
好讓你能去工作賺錢給他
so he could start you to working.
吃飯時, 他總先吃, 你只吃他剩下的
Come to eating, he ate first. Anything left over, that's what you got.
他會吃掉所有東西, 而你只分到那麼一點
Man would sit down, eat two chickens, and give you the wing.
爸, 別胡說了, 天下父母都會讓子女吃飽
You ought to stop that, pop. Everybody feed their kids.
不管時勢有多艱難, 天下父母都疼愛子女
No matter how hard times is, everybody care about their kids.
確保他們三餐溫飽
Make sure they have something to eat.
我父親唯一在意的
Only thing my daddy cared about
就是叫我們搬那一卷卷的棉花給Lubin先生
was getting them bales of cotton in to Mr. Lubin.
那是他唯一在意的事
That's the only thing that mattered to him.
以前我都在想他為何還活著
Sometimes, I used to wonder why he was still living,
為何魔鬼還沒帶走他
why the devil hadn't come and got him.
快把棉花搬到Lubin先生那
"Get them bales of cotton in to Mr. Lubin."
後來才知道我父親欠Lubin錢
Find out he owe him money.
當他知道此地不宜久留時
He should have just went on and left
他就該跑路
when he saw he couldn't get nowhere.
至少我會那樣做
That's what I would've done.
他怎留下11個孩子就走? 還有走去哪?
How he gonna leave with 11 kids? And where he gonna go?
他只懂耕作, 他根本無路可逃
He ain't knew nothing but how to farm. No, he was trapped.
我想他也知道, 但我也會為他說一句...
I think he knew it, too. But I'll say this for him...
他覺得他有責任照顧我們
He felt a responsibility toward us.
雖然不像我預期一樣體貼
May not have treated us like I felt he should have,
但他要是沒有良心
but without that responsibility,
大可以留下我們, 自己跑路
he could have run off and left us,
再另起爐灶
made his own way.
很多人也這樣
A lot of them did.
你說你父親的那一代嗎?
Back in those days, what you talkin' about?
他們每天離開房子
They walk out their front door
無論多日曬雨淋, 都在街上一直走
and take off down one road or
another and just keep on walkin'.
對, 這才像話
There you go. That's what I'm talkin' about.
一直走到他們遇到下一間房子
Just keep on walking till they come to something else.
你沒聽過大遷徙嗎? [一戰時黑人從美國南部遷北]
Ain't you never heard of nobody having the walking blues?
那就是你叫那些跑路的人
Now, that's what you call it when you just take off like that.
我父親不是你說的那種
My daddy ain't had no walking blues. What you talking about?
他留下來了
He stayed right there with his family,
但他壞事做盡
but he was just as evil as he could be!
我媽媽接受不了他和他的性格
My mama couldn't stand him. Couldn't stand that evilness.
我8歲時她就離開了
She run off when I was about eight.
她有一晚靜悄悄的走, 跟我說她會回來
She sneaked off one night, told me she was coming back for me.
自那我就再沒有見過她
I ain't never seen her no more.
他有過的女人終究都會離開他, 他不是個好人
All his women run off and left him. He wasn't good for nobody.
輪到我離家的時候
My turn come to head out.
我當時14歲
I was 14,
跟Joe Canewell的女兒打得火熱
got to sniffing around Joe Canewell's daughter.
我們家有只老騾子叫Greyboy
We had this old mule called "Greyboy".
我父親叫我出去耕作
My daddy sent me out to do some plowing.
讓我有機會跟Joe Canewell的女兒談談情
I got to fooling around with Joe Canewell's daughter.
我們找到了一個隱蔽的地方撫摸大家
Found us a nice spot, got real cozy with each other.
她當時13歲, 所以我們都知道大家發育了
She was about 13, so we done figured we grown anyway.
我們在溪河附近, 互相撫摸
So, we were down there by the creek, enjoying ourselves,
把正事都放一邊
ain't thinking about nothing.
怎料綁著Greyboy的繩子鬆開了
Didn't know Greyboy had gotten loose,
它跑回家裏, 我父親就知道事有蹊蹺
wandered back to the house, and my daddy was lookin' for me.
他找到我們時, 看到我們還在撫摸大家
So, we down there enjoying ourselves when he come up on us.
我們不知所措
Surprised us.
他拿著騾子身上的皮帶
Had them leather straps off that mule,
開始不停地打我
commenced to whupping me like there was no tomorrow.
我站起來, 當時心感侮辱又憤怒
I jump up. I'm mad, embarrassed.
又很害怕他
I was scared of my daddy.
他開始打我時
Now, when he commenced to whipping on me,
很自然地我就逃跑吧
quite naturally, I run to get out of the way.
我想他是因為我沒有完成工作而生氣
Now, I think he's mad 'cause I ain't done my work.
但我看到他故意讓我落跑
But I see where he's chasing me off,
然後想去獨佔這個女孩
so he can have the gal for himself.
當我想透了
When I see what the matter of it was,
我變得不再害怕他, 自那, 我成為了一個男人
I lost all fear of my daddy, and right there, I became a man.
才14歲
Fourteen years of age.
是時候輪到我作主了
Now, it's my turn to run him off.
我拿起他剛才用的皮帶
I picked up them same reins he used on me.
然後開始打起他來
I picked up them reins, I commenced to whupping on him.
那女孩落荒而逃
Gal jump up, she run off.
當他轉過來看著我時
When he turned to face me,
我終於知道為何魔鬼沒有帶走他
I knew why the devil never come and get him
因為他就是魔鬼
'cause he was the devil himself.
我忘了之後發生什麼了
I don't know what happened.
我醒過來, 躺在溪河旁
I woke up, laying there by the creek,
我們養的老狗Blue, 他在舔我的臉
and Blue, this old dog we had, he was licking my face.
我的雙眼腫極了
Both my eyes were swoll shut.
我以為我瞎了, 什麼都看不到
I thought I was blind, I couldn't see nothing.
就躺在那裏哭
I just laid there and cried.
我也不知道該怎辦
And I didn't know what I was gonna do.
但我知道是時候離家出走了
But I knew the time had come for me to leave my daddy's house.
突然間我感覺到世界之大
Suddenly, the world got big, and...
費了我很多時間才弄清楚
It was a long time before I could cut it down to where I could handle it.
弄清楚的期間, 我發現
Part of that cutting down was where I got to the place
其實他在我心底下, 在怒吼著想出來
where I could feel him kicking in my blood,
而我和他之所以不同
and I knew the only thing that separated us
只是我們不是生於同一個時代而已
was a matter of a few years.
Gabe叔叔, 你在吃什麼?
What you got there, Uncle Gabe?
我在吃火腿三明治
I got me a ham sandwich.
Rose給我弄了火腿三明治
Rose gave me a ham sandwich.
除了Gabriel外, 我沒再聯繫家裏的人
I lost touch with everybody except Gabriel.
但...
But...
我希望他已經死了
I hope he's dead.
我希望他能找到點安慰
I hope he found some peace.
真是個沉重的故事, 爸
That's a heavy story, pop.
我都不知道你14歲就離家了
I didn't know you left home when you was 14.
14歲太早獨立了
Fourteen's kinda young to be on your own.
要是我的話真不知道該怎辦
I don't know what I would've done.
我在那溪河站了起來, 向莫比爾出發
Well, I got up from that creek, walked on down to Mobile.
我不想再耕作了, 我想我在城市會找到更好的工作
I was through with farming.
I figured I'd do better in the cities.
所以我徒步走了200英里到莫比爾
So, I walked the 200 miles to Mobile.
等下, 你才沒有徒步走200英里, 爸
Wait a minute, you ain't walked no 200 miles, pop.
沒有人想這樣做
Ain't nobody gonna walk no 200 miles.
那是段很長的距離啊!
You talking about some walking there!
以前唯一到其他地方的方法就是徒步
That's the only way you got anywhere back in them days.
媽的, 我會選擇搭便車
Shit! Damn if I wouldn't have hitched a ride with somebody.
哪來的便車?
Who you gonna hitch it with?
那時候才沒有現在的車和科技
There ain't no cars and things like they got now.
當時是1918年
We talking about 1918.
你們在這裏聊什麼?
What you all out here gettin' into?
我跟Lyons說他現時的生活比以前好多了
I'm telling Lyons how good he got it.
他根本不知道我在說什麼
He don't know nothing about this I'm talking.
Lyons, 剛才Bonnie打來了
Lyons, that was Bonnie on the phone.
她說你約好了去接她下班
She says you supposed to pick her up.
知道了, Rose
Yeah, okay, Rose.
我到了莫比爾
I walked on down to Mobile,
搭了駛向這邊來的人便車
hitched up with some fellows that was coming up this way.
到了才發現
Got up here and found out,
不但找不到工作
not only could you not get a job,
也找不到住處
you couldn't find no place to live.
我以為自己自由了
I thought I was in freedom.
有色人種都住在裏弗班克 [加州城市]
Colored folks living down there on the Riverbanks
隨便哪裏都好
in whatever kind of shelter they could find for themselves.
有些在橋下睡
Right down there under the Brady Street Bridge.
有些在自己用木條和瀝青紙搭建的帳篷睡
Living down there in shacks made out of sticks and tar paper.
那時候我都要崩潰了
Messed around down there.
無惡不作, 開始偷竊
Went from bad to worse. Started stealing.
開始時是食物, 然後我想到偷錢
First, it was food. Then I figure I steal me some money,
可以買食物, 鞋等
I can buy me some food, buy me some shoes, too.
一樣接一樣, 最後遇見你的媽媽
One thing led to another. Met your mama.
當時還小, 急著想成為個男人
I was young, anxious to be a man.
我遇到你媽媽後有了你, 怎辦了?
I met your mama and had you. Why'd I do that for?
我得多養兩人
Now, I got to worry about feeding you and her.
得要偷更多才行
Got to steal three times as much.
我有一天在外面, 想著對誰下手
I went out one day looking for somebody to rob.
對, 我當時是個小偷
That's what I was, I was a robber.
我不會隱瞞
I'mma tell you the truth.
直至今天我還是心感慚愧, 但那是事實
I'm ashamed of it today, but it's the truth.
我找到目標, 掏出了我的小刀
I went to rob this fella, I pull out my knife.
他拿出了槍, 想也不想就射在我胸口上
He pulled out a gun, shot me in the chest.
那感覺
It felt like somebody had taken
就像有人拿著灼熱的鐵塊烙印在我身上
a hot branding iron and laid it on me.
他射了我之後, 我跳上前以小刀還擊
Now, when he shot me, I jumped at him with my knife,
他們說我殺了他
and they say I killed him.
讓我坐了15年監牢
Locked me up, put me in the penitentiary for 15 years.
我在裏面認識了Bono
That's where I met Bono.
學會了打棒球
Where I learned how to play baseball.
出來後才發現你媽媽帶走了你
Got out that place, and your mama had taken you,
在一個沒有我的環境下繼續生活
went on to make a life without me.
15年是段很長的時間
Fifteen years was a long time for her to wait.
但那15年讓我改正了
But that 15 years cured me of that robbing stuff.
Rose會告訴你
Rose'll tell you.
我再遇到她時, 她問我
I first met her, she ask me if I had
是否已經將那無知改掉了
gotten all that foolishness out of my system.
我說: 寶目, 只剩你和棒球
I said, "baby, it's you and baseball,
對我來說是重要的, 聽到嗎, Bono?
"all what count to me." You hear me, Bono?
而我也真的那樣想, 她說: 哪樣較重要?
And I meant it, too. She said, "which one come first?"
我說: 當然是棒球
I said, "well, ain't no doubt it's baseball.
但要是你留下來和我白頭到老
"But you stick and get old with me,
我們的愛會比對棒球的愛更長壽
"and we'll both outlive this baseball."
我說對了嗎, Rose?
Am I right, Rose?
那是真的
And it's true.
老兄, 閉嘴吧, 你才沒有說過
Man, hush your mouth. You ain't say no such thing.
你當時說"寶貝你知道你永遠都是最重要的"
Talkin' about, "baby, you know you'll always be number one with me."
那才是你所說的
That's what you was talking.
那就是為何我那麼愛這個女人
That's why I love this woman.
Rose總會提醒你
Rose will keep you straight.
如果你誤入歧途, 她總會提醒你
You get off the track, she'll straighten you up.
Lyons, 你快點去接Bonnie
Lyons, you better get on up and get Bonnie.
她在等你呢
She waiting on you.
- 嘿, 爸   - 什麼?
- Hey, pop.   - Yeah?
你應該來看看我表演
You ought to come down to the grill, hear me play.
老兄, 我才不去
Oh, man, I ain't goin' down there.
我太老了, 不適合到俱樂部
I'm too old to be hanging out in them clubs.
你得很出色才能在[酒吧和]烤肉店演出
You got to be good to play down at the grill.
來吧, 爸
Come on, pop.
我明天還得早起
I got to get up in the morning.
你不用待到很晚
Well, you ain't gotta stay long.
不了, 我打算吃了晚餐就去睡
No, I'm gonna eat my supper and go to bed.
那我走了, 下次見
Well, I got to go. I'll see you later.
你別在我的發薪日出現
Don't you come by my house on my payday!
還有下次來先打電話, 讓別人知道
And pick up the phone, let somebody know you coming,
也帶上Bonnie, 你知道我很想見她
and bring Bonnie, you know I'm always glad to see her.
好的, Rose, 保重
I'll do that, Rose. You take care now.
- 下次見, 爸   - 好吧
- See you, pop.    - All right.
再見, Bono先生
See you, Mr. Bono.
再見, Gabe叔叔
See you, Uncle Gabe!
Lyons! 萬獸之王!
Lyons! King of the jungle!
晚餐好了嗎, 女人?
Supper ready, woman?
我們有點事要做
Me and you got some business to take care of.
- 我會讓你爽翻天   - Troy, 我說過了
- I'mma tear it up, too.   - Troy, I done told you now!
天啊, 女人, 是Bono而已, 他就像家人一樣
Oh, hell, woman, it's Bono. Bono like family.
我已經認識這朋友...
I done know this nigger since...
- 我認識你多久了?   - 很久了
- How long have I known you?  - It's been a long time.
我自Skippy還是小朋友的時候就認識這朋友 [應為電影]
I done known this nigger since Skippy was a pup!
經歷了不少日子
Me and him done been through some times!
你說對了
You sure are right about that.
我認識他甚至比認識你還長, Rose
Hell, I known him longer than I known you, Rose,
至今我們還是好朋友
and we still standin' shoulder to shoulder.
夫復何求啊Bono
Look here, Bono, a man can't ask for no more than that.
我愛你, 朋友
I love you, nigger.
天啊別來這套, 我也愛你
Oh, hell! I love you, too.
但我得回去, 你在這裏能見你的女人
But I got to get home, see my woman. You got yours in hand.
我得回去才能見到她
I got to go get mine.
你為何這樣做, 爸?
What you do that for, pop?
Cory, 什麼事了?
What's the matter? Cory, what's the matter?
爸到學校跟Zellman教練說
Pop done went up to the school and told Coach Zellman
我不能繼續打美式足球
I can't play football no more.
也不讓我比賽和練習
Wouldn't even let me play the game.
他告訴教練叫球隊負責人別來找他
Told him to tell the recruiter not to come.
- Troy.   - 你叫我做什麼?
- Troy.   - What you Troying me for?
對, 我的確做了, 那小子知道原因
Yeah, I did it. And the boy knows why I did it.
你為何要這樣對我? 那是我唯一的機會啊!
Why you wanna do that to me? That was the one chance I had!
讓Cory打美式足球又沒什麼問題, Troy
Ain't nothing wrong with Cory playing football, Troy.
那小子欺騙了我
The boy lied to me.
我跟那臭小子說過: 你想繼續打
I told the nigger, "you want to play football,
就得繼續完成家務
"you keep up with your chores
繼續在A&P工作, 那就是條件
"hold that job down at the A&P." That was the conditions.
我去過Stawicki先生那裏...
I stopped down to see Mr. Stawicki...
賽季期間我下課後不能去工作, 爸
I can't work after school during the football season, pop.
我跟你說過Stawicki先生會為我留著位置
I tried to tell you Mr. Stawicki was holding my job for me.
你從不聽別人說話
You don't never want to listen to nobody,
然後就替我自作主張?
and then you wanna go and do this to me?
我沒對你做什麼, 這全都是你自找的
I ain't done nothin' to you. You done it to yourself.
就因為你以前沒有機會!
Just 'cause you didn't get a chance!
你只是害怕我會比你有成就, 僅此而已!
You're just scared I'm gonna be better than you, that's all!
- 來這   - Troy
- Come here.   - Troy.
Troy.
Troy
撿起它
Pick it up.
戴上它
Put it on.
系隱
Strap it up.
好了, 聽著
All right. See
你犯了個錯誤
You done made a mistake.
- 我什麼都沒做   - 我來告訴你
- I didn't even do nothing - I'll tell you what your mistake was.
你揮棒了, 但你沒打中球
You swung at the ball and you didn't hit it.
那是第一振, 你現在在打擊區
That's strike one. You in the batter's box now.
你揮棒但沒打中, 明白了嗎?
You swung and you missed, see?
那是第一振
That's strike one.
你最別被三振
Don't you strike out.
Cory, 你何不進來
Cory, why don't you come on in here,
幫我清潔一下杯櫃?
help me clean out these cupboards?
我不會退出球隊的, 我不在意爸爸說什麼
I ain't quitting the team. I don't care what papa says.
他回來後我會跟他商討的
I'll talk to him when he get back.
他得去看你叔叔Gabe
He had to go see about your Uncle Gabe.
警察又拘捕了他
Police done arrested him again.
說他擾亂秩序
Said he was disturbing the peace.
他很快回來
He'll be back directly.
進來幫我刷刷杯櫃
Come on in here and help me clean out these cupboards.
來吧
Come on.
Troy, 他們怎說了
Troy, what they say down there?
沒說什麼, 我給了他們$50, 他們就讓他走了
They ain't said nothing. I give them $50, they let him go.
晚點再跟你說
I'll talk to you about it.
Cory在哪?
Where Cory?
他在裏面幫我清潔杯櫃
He in the house, helping me clean out these cupboards.
那去叫他出來這裏
All right, tell him to get his butt out here.
他們只想要錢
All they want is the money.
我去接他回來已經六七次了
This makes six, seven times, I done went down there and got him.
他們大老遠看到我來, 就已經伸出手向我拿錢
See me coming, they stick out their hands.
我明白, 他們只在意錢
Yeah, I know what you mean.
That's all they care about, that money.
不在意對錯
They don't care about what's right.
傻子, 你為何拿了硬木材回來?
Nigger, why you got to go and get some hardwood?
你只不過是築個藩籬而已
You ain't doing nothin' but building a little old fence.
去找些松木, 那才是你需要的
Get you some soft pinewood. That's all you need.
我知道自己在做什麼, 這才是用在室外的木材
I know what I'm doing. This outside wood.
松木是用在室內的
You put pinewood inside the house.
松木是室內用的, 這些是室外的
Pinewood inside wood. This here the outside wood.
告訴我, 籓籬要建在哪?
Now tell me, where the fence gonna be?
你不需用上這種木材
You don't need this wood.
你可以用松木建
You can put it up with pinewood,
那籓籬會比你更長壽
and it'll stand as long as you gonna be here looking at it.
你怎知道我何時死, 朋友?
How you know how long I'm gonna be here, nigger?
天啊, 我可能長生不老呢
Hell, I might live forever.
我會比那老頭Horsely活得久
I'll live longer than old man Horsely.
Magee以前也總是這樣說
That's what Magee used to say.
Magee是個大傻子, 你告訴我誰會
Ah, Magee a damn fool. Now you tell me who you ever heard of
用生銹的鉗子替自己拔牙?
gonna pull their own teeth with a pair of rusty pliers?
他們是老一輩的人
They're old folks.
我祖父以前也用鉗子拔牙
My granddaddy used to pull his teeth with pliers.
以前沒有牙醫會為有色人種服務
They ain't had no dentists for colored folk back then.
至少用清潔的鉗子吧, 懂嗎?
Well, get clean pliers. You understand? Clean pliers.
先消毒, 再者, 今非昔比了
Sterilize them. Besides, we ain't living back then.
他只需要到Goldblum牙醫就行了
All he had to do was go down to Doc Goldblum's.
我看到你和那來自塔拉哈西的女孩, Alberta
I see where you and that Tallahassee gal, that Alberta,
看到你們老在一起
see where you all done got tight.
什麼意思?
What you mean, "got tight"?
我看到你經常和她打鬧
I see where you be laughing and joking with her all the time.
我跟每個人也是這樣做, 你懂我的, Bono
I laugh and joke with 'em all. Bono, you know me.
不是平常那種打鬧
Ain't the kind of laughing and joking I'm talking about.
Bono先生, 你好嗎?
How you doing, Mr. Bono?
Cory, 拿起Bono手中的木鋸開始工作
Cory, get that saw from Bono and cut some wood.
他說木材太硬很難鋸斷
He talking about wood too hard to cut.
退後點, Jim
Go on. Stand back there, Jim.
讓那小子展示給你看
Let the young boy show you how it's done.
無任歡迎
He's sure welcome to it.
看他壯得像Joe Louis一樣 [職業拳擊手]
Look at that. Big, ol' strong boy, looks like Joe Louis.
天啊, 我真的老了
Hell, I must be getting old
看到他工作才感到歲月不饒人
the way I'm watching that boy whip through that wood.
我真不懂為何媽媽想要在後院築起籓籬
I don't see why mama wants a fence around no yard no way.
我也想知道
Damn if I know, either.
我不知道她在提防什麼
I don't know what the hell she keeping out with it.
她又沒什麼別人想要的東西
She ain't got nothing nobody wants.
有些人建籓籬來提防外面的人
Some people build fences to keep people out,
有些人則用來讓圍欄內的人留住
and other people build fences to keep people in.
Rose想要留住你們, 她太愛你們了
Rose wants to hold on to you all. She loves you.
朋友, 我不需要別人來提醒我我的妻子愛我
Hell, nigger, I don't need nobody to tell me my wife loves me.
Cory, 進去找找看有沒有另一把木鋸
Cory, go in the house and see if you can find the other saw.
在哪?
Where's it at?
我說找找看, 看到你找到為止
I said find it. Look for it till you find it.
把圍欄內的人留住是什麼意思?
What is that supposed to mean? Want to keep us in?
Troy
Troy,
我幾乎大半輩子都認識你
I done known you seem like damn near my whole life.
你和Rose兩個都是, 認識很久了
You and Rose both. I known both of you all for a long time.
我還記得當初你遇見Rose的時候
I remember when you met Rose.
以前你在公園打棒球時
When you was hitting them baseball out of the park.
很多女孩都追求你
A lot of them old gals was after you then.
你簡直是萬人迷
You had the pick of the litter.
當你選了Rose, 我很替你高興
When you picked Rose, I was happy for you.
那是第一次我覺得你有點理智
That's the first time I knew you had any sense.
我想: 我的好朋友Troy知道他想要的
I said, "my man Troy knows what he's doing.
我會跟著他, 他可能會帶我到前所未到過的地方
"I'm gonna follow this nigger, he might take me somewhere."
而我真的跟著你了
I been following you, too.
我學到了一大堆關於因果的事
I done learned a whole heap of
things about life watching you.
學到了哪些是屎
I done learned how to tell where the shit lies.
哪些是苜蓿 [分辨是非]
How to tell it from the alfalfa.
你教了我很多事
You done learned me a lot of things.
教我不要重蹈覆轍
Showed me how to not make the same mistakes.
不要一步登天
To take life as it come along,
一步一步的來
keep putting one foot in front of the other.
Rose是個好女人, Troy
Rose is a good woman, Troy.
我知道
I know she a good woman.
我跟她結婚18年了
I've been married to her for 18 years.
你到底想說什麼, Bono?
What you got on your mind, Bono?
我只是說她是個好女人, 沒別的
I just say she's a good woman, like I say anything.
我不必暗示什麼
I ain't got to have nothing on my mind.
你就拋出一句她是個好女人
You just say she a good woman and leave it
然後沒有下文?
hanging out there like that?
你為何突然說她是個好女人?
Why are you telling me she a good woman?
她愛你, Troy
She loves you, Troy. Rose loves you.
你說我不配嗎?
You saying I don't measure up?
我認為那就是你想說的
That's what you tryin' to say.
我不配她因為我在和別的女人在外面
I don't measure up 'cause I'm seeing this other gal.
我知道你暗示什麼
I know what you tryin' to say.
我知道Rose對你來說有多大意義
I know what Rose means to you, Troy.
我只是想說我不想看見你對她不忠
I'm just tryin' to say I don't want to see you mess up.
我明白
Yeah.
感謝你
Well, I appreciate that, Bono.
如果你對Lucille不忠
If you was messing around on Lucille,
我也會跟你說同一番話
I'd be telling you the same thing.
那就是我要說的了
That's all I got to say.
我會說是因為我愛你們兩個
I just say that 'cause I love you both.
對
Oh. Yeah.
你懂我的為人, 我沒在外面拈花惹草
You know me. I wasn't out there looking for nothing.
我肯定你不會找到比Rose更好的女人
You can't find a better woman than Rose, I know that.
但看來Alberta總黏著我
But it seems like this woman just stuck on to me
我怎說她都不肯離開
where I can't shake her loose.
我試過跟她吵架或者避開她
I done wrestled with it and tried to throw her off,
但她反倒更纏著我了
but now she stuck on tighter.
而現在她打算這輩子跟定我了
And now she stuck on for good.
你總是告訴我你有分寸
You's in control. That's what you tell me all the time.
你會對你做過的事負責任
You responsible for what you do.
我沒在逃避責任
I ain't ducking the responsibility of it.
只要問心無愧就可以了
As long as it set right in my heart, then I'm okay.
因為那是我的宗旨, 它會告訴我是非對錯
'Cause that's all I listen to. It tell me right and wrong every time.
而我也沒說要對Rose不忠
And I ain't talking about doing Rose no bad turn.
我愛她
I love Rose.
她跟我這麼久了
She done carried me a long ways,
我為此而愛她, 尊重她
and I love and respect her for that.
我知道
I know you do.
那就是為什麼我不想看到你傷害她
That's why I don't want to see you hurt her.
但要是她發現了怎辦?
But what you gonna do when she finds out?
你到時候會剩下什麼?
What you got then?
你腳踏兩隻船
You try to juggle both of them,
早晚也得二捨其一
sooner or later, you gonna drop one of them.
- 那是常識   - 我明白, Bono
- That's common sense. - I know what you're saying, Bono.
我一直在想辦法
I been trying to figure a way to work it out.
盡快, Troy
Work it out right, Troy.
我不是想對你們的家事指指點點
I ain't trying to get all up between you and Rose's business,
但趁事情還沒轉壞前趕快解決
but work it, so it come out right.
那我來介入你們的家事
Hell, I get all between you and Lucille's business.
你打算何時買
And when you gonna buy that woman
她一直想要的冰箱?
that refrigerator she be wanting?
別告訴我你沒錢
And don't tell me you ain't got no money.
我知道誰替你打理財務
I know who your banker is.
錢該花在Lucille的冰箱上而不是放在梅隆銀行內
Mellon don't need that money as bad as Lucille wants that refrigerator.
我很清楚
I know that.
- 告訴你吧   - 什麼?
- Tell you what I'll do.   - What?
當你為Rose建成籓籬時
When you finish building this fence for Rose,
我就給Lucille買冰箱
I'll buy Lucille that refrigerator.
你會後悔的
You done stuck your foot in your mouth now.
朋友, 你要去哪?
Hey, nigger, where you going?
我得回家
I'm going home.
你不是在想我會幫你吧
I know you don't expect me to help you now.
我得保住我的錢
I'm protecting my money.
我想看你一個人慢慢的建
I want to see you put that fence up by yourself.
那就是我想看的
That's what I want to see.
沒有我的幫忙, 六個月後你仍然毫無頭緒
You'll be here another six months without me.
朋友, 那樣不對啊
Nigger, you ain't right.
當談到我的錢
When it come to my money,
我就像國慶日的煙火一樣對[好]
I'm right as fireworks on the Fourth of July.
等著瞧
We gonna see.
你準備去提款吧!
You better get out your bank book!
他們在警局在說了什麼? Gabe怎了?
What they say down there? What's happening with Gabe?
我過去接回他了, 花了我五十塊
I went down there and got him out. Cost me $50.
說他在擾亂秩序
Said he was disturbing the peace.
法官三周後審訊
Judge set up a hearing for him in three weeks
他為何不被重新分配到醫院內
to show cause why he shouldn't be recommitted.
那你怎說? 你怎跟法官說的
What'd you say? What'd you tell the judge?
我跟他說我會照顧他
I told him I'd take care of him.
沒有理由又分配他住醫院
It didn't make no sense to recommit the man.
他伸出他那貪婪的手
He stuck out his big greasy palm,
跟我說交出$50然後帶他回家
told me to give him $50 and take him on home.
那他現在在哪?
Where's he at now? Where'd he go off to?
又到處亂跑了, 他不想別人拖著他的手
Gone about his business. He don't need nobody to hold his hand.
我也不知道, 但那看來是最好的選擇
Well, I don't know, seem like that would be the best place for him.
讓他住在醫院裏
To put him in a hospital.
我知道你接下來要說什麼
I know what you say gonna say,
但那正是我認為這樣做是對的原因
but that's what I think would be best.
那他在打仗時失去的一切, 為了什麼?
Man had his life ruined fighting for what?
現在他們想把他鎖起來?
Now, they want to take him and lock him up?
該給他自由啊, 他又沒打擾誰
Let him be free. Man ain't bothering nobody.
我想每個人都有不同的看法
Everybody got their own way of looking at it, I guess.
來拿你的午餐吧
Come on, get your lunch.
我這裏有些棉豆和玉米麵包
I got some lima beans and cornbread in the oven.
快去, 你得吃點什麼
Come on, get somethin' to eat.
在這裏煩惱Gabe的事也沒幫助
Ain't no sense in you fretting over Gabe.
Rose, 我有點事要跟你說
Rose, I got something to tell you.
- 待我把食物放好再說   - Rose...
- Wait till I put the food on the table. - Rose...
我不知道該怎開口
Now, I don't know how to tell you this.
但又不能瞞著你
And I can't explain it none.
[好感]就那麼一點點的積聚啊
It just sort of grows on you.
開始時就像小木灌
It started off like a little bush,
待你發現時已經是整片森林了
next thing you know, it's a whole forest.
Troy, 你在說什麼?
Troy, what is you talking about?
我在說話, 女人, 讓我把話說完
I'm talking, woman. Let me talk.
我在跟你說
I'm trying to tell you,
我在找個隱晦的方法跟你說...
find a way to tell you that...
我要成為父親了
I'm gonna be a daddy.
對, 我要成為別人的父親了
Yeah, I'm gonna be somebody's daddy.
Troy, 不是真的吧? 你要成為什麼?
Troy, you ain't telling me this. You're gonna be what?
- 你要成為別人的父親?   - Rose...
- You're gonna be somebody's daddy?   - Rose...
你竟然跟你的妻子說這個?
You're telling your wife this?
現在...
Now...
嗨, Troy, 嗨, Rose
Hey, Troy! Hey, Rose!
我等了18年就為了聽你說這些事嗎?
I got to wait 18 years to hear something like this?
嗨, Rose
Hey, Rose.
我有朵花送給你
I got a flower for you.
那是朵玫瑰花, 就像你的名字一樣
That's a rose. The same rose like you is.
謝了, Gabe
Thanks, Gabe.
Troy, 你沒在生我的氣吧?
Troy, you ain't mad at me?
那些壞人抓了我回來
Them bad mens come and put me away.
- 你沒在生我的氣吧?   - 沒, 我沒有生氣
- You ain't mad at me?   - No. No, I ain't mad at you.
18年了, 你竟然做得出這種事?
Eighteen years, and you want to come with this?
看我拿到了什麼? 一個全新的25美分
See what I got? Got a brand-new quarter.
Rose, 只是...
Rose, it's just that...
你沒什麼可以說, 也不用解釋
Ain't nothing you can say, Troy. Ain't no explaining it.
給我這25美分的人還有一大堆
The fella that give me this quarter had a whole mess of 'em!
我要留著它直到它暗啞無光
I'm gonna keep this quarter till it stops shining.
Gabe, 出去前門等我, 我冰箱裏有西瓜
Gabe, go on up front now.
I got some watermelon in the frigidaire.
快去, 我待會拿給你
Go on. I'll get you a piece.
Rose, 聽我說, 我當時在追趕地獄之犬
Say, Rose, you know, I was chasing hellhounds,
然後那些壞人把我抓回去鎖起來了
and them bad mens come and get me and take me away.
Troy救了我, 他來了並跟他們說
Troy helped me. He come down there and told them
他們最好在他打跨他們之前放了我
they better let me go before he beat them up!
他真的說了
Yeah, he did!
出去吧, Gabe, 我待會給你西瓜
Go up front now, Gabe. I'll get you some watermelon.
那些壞人都走了
Them bad men is gone now.
好吧, Rose要給我西瓜
Okay. Rose gonna give me some watermelon,
有條紋的那種
the kind with the stripes on it.
為什麼, Troy?
Why, Troy?
為什麼?
Why?
過了那麼多年, 你現在跟我說這些?
After all these years, you come dragging this in to me now?
你這年紀, 不應該會做的
It don't make no sense at your age.
我可以理解你十年或者十五年前這樣做, 但不是現在
I could've expected this 10, or 15 years ago, but not now.
年齡與此沒有關係, Rose
Age ain't got nothing to do with it, Rose.
我做了一個妻子該做的
I done tried to be everything a wife should be.
一個妻子可以做的所有事
Everything a wife could be.
我結婚整整18年了
I've been married 18 years,
而現在竟到了你說
and now, I got to live to see the day you tell me
你和別的女人有了孩子的一天
you been seeing another woman and done fathered a child by her.
你明知道我不喜歡同父異母什麼的
And you know I never wanted no half-nothing in my family!
我整個家庭都是這樣
My whole family is half.
每個人都有不同的父母親
Everybody got different fathers and mothers
我的幾個兄弟姊妹都是這樣
and my two sisters and my brothers.
你根本不知道誰是誰生的
You could hardly tell who's who.
永遠不能好好談談父母的話題
Could never sit down and talk about papa and mama.
因為大家的父母都不一樣
It was always your papa, your mama, my papa, my mama.
我從不想我的孩子們也是這樣
And I ain't never wanted that for none of my children!
然而現在, 你竟然過來
And now, you want to drag your behind in here
跟我說這些事!
and tell me something like this!
夠了, 你有權利知道的, 是時候了
Stop it now. You ought to know. It's time for you to know.
我才不想知道, 媽的!
Well, I don't want to know, god damn it!
Rose?
我不能讓她墮胎, 米已成炊了
I just can't make it go away. It's done now.
我沒法改變事情
I can't wish the circumstances of the thing away.
你也不想改變
And you don't want to, either.
或許你想我們兩母子離開
Maybe you want to wish me and my boy away.
也許那就是你想的
Maybe that's what you want.
你不能這樣做
Well, you can't wish us away.
我把我的18年放在你身上了
I got 18 years of my life invested in you.
你該留在我們的床上而不是出去鬼混
You ought to have stayed upstairs in my bed where you belong.
聽著, 我們可以處理好這事
Now, listen to me. We can get a handle on this thing.
我們可以說清楚, 有共識
We can talk this out, come to an understanding.
突然間此事就是關於"我們"
All of a sudden it's "we."
當你在外面
Where was "we" at when
you were down there,
跟那個可惡的女人鬼混時"我們"在哪裏?
rolling around with some godforsaken woman?
"我們"該在你做傻事之前
"We" should've come to an understanding
就要有共識!
before you started making a damn fool of yourself!
當說到共識時
You're a day late and a dollar short
你總是遲了
when it comes to an understanding with me.
Rose, 只是因為她能給我完全不同的感覺
Rose, it's just that she...gives me a different idea.
完全不同的自我理解
A different understanding about myself.
讓我可以在這裏走出去時, 放下所有壓力
I can step out of this house and get away from the pressures
和問題, 變成一個完全不同的人
and the problems, be a different man.
我不用擔心如何修好屋頂
I ain't got to worry about how I'll get the roof fixed,
或者付錢, 或者...
or pay the bills, or...
我可以
I can just
成為一個我前所未有過的自己
be a part of myself I ain't never been before.
我想知道的是...
What I want to know is...
我想知道的是
What I want to know
你是否打算繼續見她?
is do you plan to continue seeing her?
那就是你可以說的
That's all you can say to me.
我在她的家裏能放鬆下來
I could sit up in her house and laugh.
你明白嗎?
You understand what I'm saying?
我可以放聲笑, 而那感覺真好
I could laugh out loud, and it feels good.
簡直好到了我心底裏
It reaches all the way down to the bottom of my shoes.
Rose, 我...
Rose, I...
我不想放棄那些
I can't give that up.
那或許你該繼續留在她那裏
Well, maybe you ought to go on and stay down there with her,
如果她真是比我更好的女人的話
if she's a better woman than me.
這不是關於誰是更好的女人的問題
It ain't about nobody being a better woman, or nothing.
Rose, 你盡責了
Rose, you ain't to blame.
做妻子的話你簡直是不二之選
A man couldn't ask for a better wife than you've been.
這事我得負起所有責任
I'm responsible for it.
我每天重複做著同樣的事
I done locked myself into a pattern,
照顧你們, 都讓我忘了自己了
trying to take care of you all, that I forgot about myself.
我不是一直在你背後嗎?
Well, what the hell was I there for?
那是我的工作, 不是他人的
That was my job, not somebody else's.
Rose, 聽著, 我竭盡所能去過正當的生活
Rose, listen to me. I done tried all my life to live decent.
一個正當, 努力向上的生活
To live a clean, hard, useful life.
我盡了力去成為一個好丈夫
I try to be a good husband to you, in every way I know how.
可能我一開始就錯了吧, 我不知道
Maybe I come into the world backwards, I don't know,
但你就像上場前已經被二振了一樣
but you're born with two strikes on you before you come to the plate.
你得把任何事都看管好
You got to guard it closely,
老是擔心突發事情
always looking for the curveball on the inside corner.
你不能讓任何事不受你控制
You can't afford a called strike.
你不能讓任何事漏掉
You can't let nothing get past you.
要是你倒下了, 你還不死心
If you're going down, you're doing down swinging.
所有事都像對著你干一樣
Everything lined up against you!
你還想怎樣?
What you gonna do?
我贏了他們, Rose, 我短打了 [犧牲]
I fooled them, Rose. I bunted.
當我有你和Cory和份有點像樣的工作, 我很安全
When I found you and Cory and a halfway decent job, I was safe.
沒什麼可以拖累我了
Couldn't nothing touch me!
我不會再被三振出局
I wasn't gonna strike out no more.
不會再回去坐牢
I wasn't going back to the penitentiary.
不會再喝醉, 睡在街上
I wasn't gonna lie in the street with a bottle of wine.
我安全了, 我有個家庭, 有份工作
I was safe. I had me a family, a job.
我不會被三振的
I wasn't gonna get that last strike.
我站在一壘
I was standing on first base,
等著回到本壘
waiting for one of them boys to
knock me in, to bring me home.
你該留在我們的床上, Troy
You should have stayed in my bed, Troy.
然後我看到那女子, 她讓我膽大起來
Then I saw the gal, she firmed up my backbone.
我在想如果我努力點, 或許可以盜壘
I got to thinkin' that if I tried, maybe I could steal second.
- 你明白嗎?   - 你該抱緊我
- You understand what I'm saying? - You should've held me tight.
你該捉緊我的手
You should've grabbed me and held on.
我站在一壘18年了
I stood on first base for 18 years,
然後我想, 管他的, 豁出去
and I thought, well, god damn it, go on for it!
我們不是在說棒球啊!
We ain't talking about baseball!
我們在說你跟別的女人鬼混
We talking about you going off and laying up with another woman,
然後把這事帶回家跟我說
then bringing it home to me.
那才是我們要討論的
That's what we're talking about.
- 我們不是要談棒球!   - Rose, 你沒細心聽
- We're not talkin' about no baseball! - Rose, you're not listening to me.
我在用我最擅長的東西去表達
I'm trying to explain it to you the best way I know how.
對我來說很難去接受
It's not easy for me to admit
我站在原地18年了這事實
that I've been standing in the same place for 18 years!
我也跟你一起站在原地啊!
Well, I've been standing with you!
我一直都跟你站在原地, Troy! 我也有我的人生
I've been right here with you, Troy! I got a life, too.
我為此付出了我的18年啊
I gave 18 years of my life to stand in the same spot as you!
你沒想過我也想要做其他事?
Don't you think I ever wanted other things?
沒想過我也有我的夢想和願望?
Don't you think I had dreams and hopes?
那我的生命呢? 那我呢?
What about my life? What about me?
你以為我沒有想過
Don't you think it ever crossed my mind
去認識其他男人?
to want to know other men?
或者一走了之
That I wanted to lay up somewhere
忘了我的職責?
and forget about my responsibilities?
或者我想有過人讓我笑
That I wanted someone to make me laugh,
讓我快樂?
so I could feel good?
你不是唯一一個有需求的人
You're not the only one who's got wants and needs.
但我留下來了, Troy
But I held on to you, Troy.
我把我的所有情感, 需求和夢想
I took all my feelings, my wants and needs and dreams,
埋藏在你的心底下
and I buried them inside you.
我把種子埋藏好, 每天看著它, 祈望它成長
I planted a seed and watched and prayed over it.
我把自己埋藏在你心內然後等待開花!
I planted myself inside you and waited to bloom!
但那花了我18年時間
And it didn't take me no 18 years
才知道那泥土原來如石頭般硬
to realize the soil was hard and rocky,
還有它根本不會開花!
and it wasn't never gonna bloom!
但我仍然捉緊你, 我把你捉得更緊
But I held on to you, Troy. I held you tighter.
你是我的丈夫
You was my husband.
我該給你我的全部
I owed you everything I had.
我的每一部分
Every part of me I could find to give you.
當晚上我在樓上的睡房時
And upstairs in that bedroom, with the darkness falling in on me,
我用盡力氣消除那個疑慮
I gave everything I had to try and erase the doubt
那個其實你不是個好男人的疑慮
that you wasn't the finest man in the world.
無論你打算去哪裏, 我都會跟著你
And wherever you was going, i was gonna be there with you,
因為你是我的丈夫
because you was my husband.
因為這樣做我才能繼續做你的妻子
'Cause that's the only way I was gonna survive as your wife.
你經常說給什麼
You always talking about what you give
還有你不能給什麼
and what you don't have to give.
但你也會拿取, Troy
But you take, too, Troy.
你會拿取而且不在乎是誰付出的
You take and don't even know nobody's giving.
你說我好逸惡勞
You say I take and don't give.
- Troy, 你弄痛我了   - 你說我好逸惡勞
- Troy, you're hurting me.   - You say I take and don't give.
- Troy, 我的手很痛, 放手!   - 我給了我能給的
- Troy, you're hurting my arm, let go!
- I gave you everything I got.
別說我沒有
Don't you tell that lie on me.
- 媽媽!   - 別說我沒有
- Mama!   - Don't you tell that lie!
Troy, 我弄痛我了!
Troy, you're hurting me!
Troy! Troy!
好了, 那是二振
All right. That's strike two.
你別再惹我, 你最好別三振
You stay away from around me, boy. Don't you strike out.
你滿球數了
You're living with a full count.
你最好別三振!
Don't you strike out!
Troy, 我想跟你說點事
Troy, I want to talk to you.
突然間?
All of a sudden?
過了這麼久你想跟我說點事?
After all this time, you want to talk to me, huh?
你數個月來沒跟我說過一句話
You ain't wanted to talk to me in months.
昨晚也沒有
You ain't wanted to talk to me last night.
你那時可不想理會我
You didn't want no parts of me then.
現在你想來說什麼?
What you want to talk to me about now?
明天是星期五
Tomorrow's Friday.
我知道
I know what day tomorrow is.
你以為我不知道嗎?
You think I don't know tomorrow's Friday?
我的整生, 都在等星期五的來臨
My whole life, I ain't done nothing but look to see Friday coming,
你還來提醒我
and you got to tell me it's Friday.
我想知道你會否回家
I want to know if you're coming home.
我每天都回家, 你知道的
I always come home, Rose. You know that.
沒有一晚我是沒回來的
Ain't never been a night I ain't come home.
你明知道那不是我的意思
That ain't what I mean, and you know it.
我想知道你下班後會否直接回家
I wanna know if you're coming straight home after work.
我想我會兌換支票, 然後在Taylor的酒吧和他們喝點酒
I figured I'd cash my check,
hang out at Taylors' with the boys.
或許玩一局[西洋]跳棋
Maybe play a game of checkers.
Troy, 我不能再繼續這樣, 我接受不了
Troy, I can't live like this. I won't live like this.
自那之後你就人在心不在
You're living on borrowed time with me.
六個月以來, 你都沒真正回來
Been going on six months now, you ain't been coming home.
我每晚都回來, 一年來從沒間斷過
I come home every night. Every night of the year.
那就整整365天
That's 365 days.
我想你明天下班後直接回家
I want you to come home tomorrow after work.
Rose, 你知道我不會亂花錢
Rose, I don't mess up my pay. You know that.
我收到工資後就全數交給你
I take my pay, i give it to you.
我只拿著你分配給我的部份
I don't have no money but what you give me back.
我只想要一點私人時間而已
I just want a little time to myself.
去享樂一下
A little time to enjoy life.
那我呢? 何時才輪到我去享樂?
What about me? When's my time to enjoy life?
我不知道還可以說什麼, 我已經盡力了
I don't know what to tell you, Rose. I'm doing the best I can.
你下班回家後
You ain't been comin' home from work,
只換件衣服又出去了
but time enough to change your clothes and run out.
你叫那盡力嗎?
You wanna call that the best you can do?
我晚點得去醫院看Alberta
I'm going over to the hospital to see Alberta.
她今天下午進了醫院
She went into the hospital this afternoon.
看來是早產
Looks like she might have the baby early.
我不會去太久
I won't be gone long.
你該知道他們今天到了Pearl小姐那裏
Well, you ought to know. They went over to Miss Pearl's
帶走了Gabe
and got Gabe today.
她說你叫他們鎖起他來
She said you told them to go ahead and lock him up.
我才沒有說過, 你被她騙了
I ain't said no such thing. Whoever told you that is telling a lie.
Pearl小姐撒了個很大的謊
Miss Pearl ain't doing nothing but telling a big, fat lie.
她不用說出口, 我在文件上看到的
She ain't had to tell me. I read it on the papers.
- 那份文件說了什麼?   - 說你叫他們去帶走他
- What'd it say, huh?   - It said you told them to take him.
那他們肯定弄錯了
Oh, well, then they screwed that up,
就像他們弄錯其他事一樣
just like they screw up everything.
我才不在意他們在文件上說了什麼
I ain't worried about what they got on that paper.
說政府會把他的部分財產交給醫院作照顧費用
It say the government sends part of the check to the hospital,
另一部份交給你
the other part to you.
我跟此事毫無關係
I ain't got nothing to do with that, if that's the way it works.
我也沒叫他們分給我
I don't make up the rules...
你對待Gabe就像你對待Cory一樣差勁
You did Gabe just like you did Cory.
你不會替Cory簽署
You wouldn't sign the paper for Cory,
但你卻替Gabe簽了, 是你簽的!
but you signed for Gabe! You signed that paper!
我說過我沒有簽署過什麼, 女人
I told you I ain't signed nothing, woman.
天啊, 我只簽了份釋放同意書
Hell, the only thing I signed was the release form.
我又不識字
Hell, I can't read,
天知道他們在同意書上寫了什麼
I don't know what they had on that paper.
我才沒簽過什麼送走Gabe的文件
I ain't signed nothing about sending Gabe away.
我當時說送他到醫院, 你說要讓他自由
I said send him to the hospital, you said let him go free.
現在你反過來
Then you went down there
同意送他到醫院, 就為了他的錢
and you signed him to the hospital for half his money.
這是自相矛盾, Troy
You went back on yourself, Troy.
你會有報應的
You're gonna have to answer for that.
你才跟Pearl小姐說過話
You just been over there talking to Miss Pearl.
她只是因為不能再
She just mad 'cause she ain't gettin'
騙Gabe的錢而生氣, 所以胡說而已
Gabe's rent money, that's all it is.
Troy, 我親眼看著你簽的!
Troy, I seen where you signed the paper!
你才沒有!
You ain't seen nothing I signed!
那她家裏為何又有我弟弟的文件?
And what she doing got papers on my brother for, anyway?
Pearl小姐只是在撒謊
Miss Pearl ain't doing nothing but telling a big, fat lie,
我會去跟她對質!
and I'm gonna tell her about it, too!
我沒有簽署過什麼!
You ain't seen nothing I signed!
還說我...
Say...
我沒有簽署過什麼!
You ain't seen nothing I signed!
Troy.
那是醫院打來說Alberta生下來了
That was the hospital. Alberta had the baby.
是嗎? 是男還是女的?
Yeah? What she have? What is it?
是個女孩
It's a girl.
我...
I...
我該去看她一下
I better get on down there to see her.
Troy.
- Troy   - 我總得去看她一下吧, Rose
- Troy. - I got to go see her now, Rose. That's only right.
怎麼了? 嬰兒什麼有問題嗎?
What's the matter? Baby all right, ain't it?
Alberta產後死去了
Alberta died having the baby.
你說她死了?
She died? You say she's dead?
她死了?
Alberta dead?
他們說盡了力, 他們...
They said they done all they could. They...
他們對她無能為力
They couldn't do nothing for her.
那嬰兒呢? 她還好嗎?
Oh, what about the baby? Baby all right?
他們說她很健康
They say it's healthy.
我在想誰會替她辦身後事
I wonder who's gonna bury her.
她有家人的, Rose
She had a family, Rose.
她不是無親無故
She wasn't living in the world by herself.
我當然知道
I know she wasn't living in the world by herself.
你下一樣想知道的就是她有沒有保險
Next thing you wanna know if she had any insurance.
你沒資格跟我這樣說話!
You ain't got to talk to me like that!
你第一樣關心的就是: 誰會埋葬她?
First thing that jumped out your mouth. "Who's gonna bury her?"
生怕我會付錢替她辦理
Like I'm finna take that task on for myself.
我是你的妻子, 別推開我
I'm your wife. Don't push me away.
我沒有推開誰, 就給我點空間
I ain't pushing nobody away. Just give me some space.
讓我靜一下
Just give me some room to breathe.
好了, 死神先生
All right, Mr. Death.
我來告訴你接下來的事
I tell you what I'm gonna do.
我會繼續
I'm gonna take
在這後院築起籓籬, 知道嗎?
and build me a fence around this yard, see?
我會築起籓籬保護屬於我的東西
I'm gonna build me a fence around what belongs to me.
然後我想你留在另一邊
And then I want you to stay on the other side.
直至你準備好帶走我
You stay over there till you're ready for me,
到時候你就儘管來吧
then you come on.
帶上你的軍隊, 鐮刀, 披上你的袍子
Bring your army, bring your sickle, bring your wrestling clothes.
這次我不會鬆懈
I ain't gonna fall down on my vigilance this time.
你不會...
You ain't gonna...
你不會就有機可乘
You ain't gonna sneak up on me no more.
當你準備好時
When you ready for me,
當你手上的名單寫著Troy Maxson時
when the top of your list say Troy Maxson,
到時候你就正面而來吧
then you come on up and knock on the front door.
其他人與此無關
Ain't nobody else got nothing to do with this.
這是你我之間的事
This between you and me.
男人之間!
Man to man!
你在準備好帶走我之前留在籓籬的另一邊!
You stay on the other side of that fence till you ready for me!
然後隨時都可以
Then you come up and knock on that front door
與我正面對決!
anytime you want!
我拭目以待
I'll be ready for you.
Rose?
我在抱著我的女孩
I'm standing here with my daughter in my arms.
聽著
Now,
她只不過是一個
she ain't but a wee,
初生的嬰兒而已
bitty little old thing.
她跟大人間的事沒有關係
She don't know nothing about grownfolk business.
她是無辜的
She innocent,
但她沒有母親
and she ain't got no mama.
你為何告訴我這些, Troy?
What you telling me for, Troy?
那...
Well...
我們在外面門廊好了
Guess we'll go sit out here on the porch.
一個男人應該做他認為正確的事
A man's got to do what's right for him.
我毫不後悔我做過的事
I ain't sorry for nothing I done.
我內心感到那是對的事
It felt right in my heart.
小寶寶在笑什麼?
What you smiling at?
你父親是個年紀老邁的好人
Your daddy's a great, big ol' man.
無所畏懼, 但有時候也難免會害怕
Got these great big ol' hands, but sometimes he's scared.
而現在你父親正正在害怕
And right now, your daddy's scared 'cause we
因為我們只能在這門廊坐著, 無家可歸
sitting out here on the porch and ain't got no home.
我也試過居無定所
Oh, I've been homeless before.
但我沒試過帶著嬰兒無家可歸
I ain't never had no baby with me, but I've been homeless.
就只是寂寞的在外面流連
You just be out there on the road by your lonesome
看著列車一架一架
and just see one of them trains coming by
來了又走...
and just kinda go, say...
她是我的女兒, Rose, 是我的...
She's my daughter, Rose, and my...
我的親生骨肉, 我不能遺棄她
My own flesh and blood. I can't deny her.
就像我不能遺棄我的兒子們
No more than I can deny them boys.
你們幾母子都是我的家人
You and them boys is my family.
你們, 還有這孩子就是我唯一擁有的, 所以...
You, them, and this child is all I got in this world, so...
我想我要說的是
I guess what I'm saying is,
如果你能替我照顧她, 我會很感謝你
that I'd appreciate it if you was to help me take care of her.
好吧, Troy
Okay, Troy,
你是對的
you're right.
我會替你照顧你的孩子
I'll take care of your baby for you.
因為如你所說
'Cause, like you say,
她是無辜的
she innocent.
總不能把父親的罪名降到孩子身上
You can't visit the sins of the father upon the child.
況且單親孩子的日子會很艱難
Motherless child's got a hard time.
從今起, 這孩子有個母親了
From right now, this child's got a mother.
但你是個寡夫
But you're a womanless man.
大家都避開我
I'm coming in, everybody going out.
我得帶這蛋糕到教堂的蛋糕義賣
I'm taking this cake down to the church for the bake sale.
Lyons剛來過看你, 想要還你的二十塊
Lyons was by to see you. He stopped by to pay you your $20.
錢就在桌上
It's laying right here on the table.
拿著, 是我的工資
Well, here go this money.
放在桌上吧, Troy, 我晚點處理
Well, put it in there on the table, Troy. I'll get it.
你什麼時候回來?
What time you coming back?
你在這裏問東問西也沒用
Ain't no use in you studyin' me.
我何時回來也沒關係
Don't matter what time I come back.
我只是問一下而已, 女人, 現在都不給問了嗎?
I just asked you a question, woman. Can't I ask you a question?
Troy, 我不想吵架
Troy, I don't want to get into it.
你的餐在爐子裏
Now, your food is in there on the stove.
翻熱一下就好了
All you got to do is heat it up.
還有別吃掉蛋糕
And don't be eating the rest of them cakes in there now.
我還得用
I'm coming back for them.
明天下午也有蛋糕義賣
We're having a bake sale at the church tomorrow.
[工資]
嗨, Troy
Hey, Troy.
怎了, Bono?
What's happening, Bono?
只是想來看看你
I just thought I'd stop by to see you.
你家裏沒人, 所以我猜...
Wasn't no one at the house, so I figured...
為什麼?
What you stop by to see me for?
你很久沒來看我了
You ain't stopped by in a month of Sundays.
天啊, 我肯定欠了你錢還是什麼的
Hell, I must owe you some money or somethin'.
你還說, 自從你升職後我都快跟不上你了
Well, since you got your promotion, I can't keep up with you.
以前早晚都看到你
Used to see you every day.
現在我甚至不知道你在哪工作
Now I don't even know what route you working.
他們老是調配我到不同地方工作
Keep switching me around.
現在我負責白人的街區
Got me out there in green tree now, hauling white folk garbage.
- 白人街區嗎?   - 對
- Green tree, huh?   - Yeah.
你真幸運
You lucky.
至少你不用搬垃圾
At least you ain't got to be lifting them barrels.
該死的, 它們越來越重
Damn if they ain't getting heavier.
我再多工作兩年就退休了
I'm gonna put in my two years and call it quits.
對, 我也在想退休的事
Yeah, I'm thinking about retiring myself.
你的工作輕鬆多了
Oh, you got it easy.
你可以再多駕駛五年啊
You could drive for another five years.
那可不同, Bono
Ain't the same, Bono.
駕駛不像搬垃圾
It ain't like working the back of the truck.
只能獨自工作, 沒人聊天
You feel like you working by yourself. Ain't nobody to talk to.
不了, 還是退休吧, Lucille最近怎樣?
Naw, I'm thinking about retiring. How's Lucille?
她很好
She all right.
她的關節炎有時候會復發
Her arthritis get to acting up on her sometimes.
我過來時看到Rose, 她在教堂嗎?
Saw Rose on the way here. She going down to the church, huh?
對, 她過去了
Yeah, she took up going down there.
那些傳教士只想撈油水而已
All them preachers looking to fatten their pockets.
這裏有琴酒
Got some gin in here.
不了謝謝, 我只是來看看你
No, thanks. I just stopped in to say hello.
你也可以喝一杯啊朋友, 我從沒...
Well, you can take a drink, nigger. I ain't...
認識你以來從沒看過你不喝酒
I ain't never known you to say no to a drink.
你明天又不用上班
You ain't got to work tomorrow.
我只是來一下而已
I just stopped by.
我在想晚點到Skinner家裏
I'm thinkin' of going over to Skinner's.
我們每星期五都會在他家裏玩多米諾骨牌
We got us a domino game going over his house every Friday.
朋友, 你才不會玩什麼多米諾骨牌
Nigger, you can't play no dominoes.
我以前老是贏你
I used to whup you four games out of five.
我吸取了教訓, 我玩牌的技術在進步
Well, that learned me. I'm getting better.
是嗎?
Yeah?
好吧
That's all right.
我得走了
Look here, I got to be getting on.
有空來找我一下?
Stop by sometime, huh?
我會的, Bono
Yeah, I'll do that, Bono.
Lucille跟Rose說你給她買了個新冰箱
Lucille told Rose you, uh, got her that new refrigerator.
對啊, Rose跟Lucille說你終於把籓籬建好了
Yeah. Rose told Lucille you had finally built your fence,
所以我想我們就扯平了
so, I figured we'd call it even.
我就知道你信守承諾
I knew you would.
是啊
Yeah.
好了
Okay.
再見
I'll be talking to you.
很高興看到你, Bono
Yeah, good to see you, Bono.
我有空會來找你的
I'm gonna stop over.
好吧, Troy
Yeah. Okay, Troy.
[美國海軍陸戰隊招募署]
我要進去
I got to get by.
你說什麼?
Say what? What you say?
你擋著我了, 我得進去
You in my way. I got to get by.
你得去哪?
You got to get by where?
這是我付錢買的房子
This is my house. Bought and paid for.
花了我15年之久, 如果你想進我的房子
Took me 15 years, and if you want to go in my house
而我坐在家門樓梯上的話, 你該說"請讓一下"
and I'm sitting on the steps, you say, "excuse me,"
就像你媽媽教你那樣
like your mama taught you.
得了吧, 爸, 我得進去
Come on, pop, I gotta get by.
你想就這樣無視我?
You just gonna walk over the top of me?
我也在這裏住的
I live here, too.
你想在我的地方無視我?
You just gonna walk over the top of me in my own house?
我不怕你
I ain't scared of you.
我沒在問你是否害怕我
I ain't asked you if you was scared of me.
我是問你是否要在
I asked you was you finna walk over the top of me
我的地方無視我? 那才是我問的
in my own house? That was the question.
你不會說"請讓一下"
You ain't gonna say, "excuse me."
你就這樣無視我
You just gonna walk over the top of me.
隨便你怎說
If you want to put it like that.
我怎說了?
How else am I gonna put it?
我是想繞過你進去
I was walking by you to go into the house,
因為你醉了, 在樓梯上唱歌
'cause you sitting on the steps drunk, singing to yourself.
- 你也可以這樣說   - 也不說"請讓一下"?
- You can put it like that.   - Without saying, "excuse me"?
我問你了, 也不說"請讓一下"?
I asked you a question. Without saying, "excuse me"?
我不用對你客氣
I ain't got to say "excuse me" to you.
你在這個家裏不重要了
You don't count around here no more.
我懂了, 我在這裏不重要了
Oh, I see. I don't count around here no more.
你也不用跟你的父親客氣了
You ain't got to say "excuse me" to your daddy.
突然間, 你就可以作主
All of a sudden, you done got so grown,
認為你父親在這裏不重要對吧?
where your daddy don't count around here no more, huh?
在他辛勞工作才得以
Around here in his own house and yard
買回來的地方嗎?
that he done paid for with the sweat of his brow?
突然間, 你就可以作主
All of a sudden, you done got so grown
認為你父親在這裏毫無地位
that your daddy don't even count around here.
你要成為一家之主嗎?
What, you gonna take over?
你要接管我的屋子嗎? 你要拿走我的東西嗎?
You gonna take over my house? You gonna wear my pants?
你要睡在我的床上嗎?
You gonna go in there and stretch out on my bed?
你認為你不用再對你父親客氣
You ain't got to say, "excuse me,"
因為他在這裏毫無地位
because your daddy don't count around here no more.
- 對嗎?   - 正是
- Is that right?   - That's right.
你老是說這種蠢事
You always talking this dumb stuff.
為何不放過我一下?
Now why don't you just get out my way?
我猜你有自己的房子了
I guess you got some place to sleep.
也能夠養活自己, 你能嗎?
Something to put in your belly. You got that?
因為那就是你需要做到的, 你能嗎?
'Cause that's what you need. You got that?
你不知道我有什麼能耐! 你也沒有權利過問!
You don't know what I got! You ain't got to worry about what I got!
你說得對
You right.
完全正確
You 100% right.
十七年來我一直都照顧你, 擔心你
I done spent the last 17 years worrying about what you got.
所以現在輪到你作主了嗎?
Now, it's your turn, see?
我跟你說清楚現在的情況
I tell you what we do.
你長大了, 我們都知道吧
You grown. We done established that.
你說你是成人, 現在就看看你到底是不是
You a man. Now, let's see you act like one.
你現在轉身離開這裏
Turn your behind around and walk out this yard.
當你走出巷子時
And when you get out there in the alley,
你把這間屋子拋諸腦後
you can forget about this house, see.
因為這是我的房子
'Cause this is my house.
你出去, 成為你所謂的大人, 然後找個地方住
You go on and be a man and get your own house.
你可以把這一切忘掉, 因為這都是我的
You can forget about this, 'cause this is mine.
你出去過你的生活, 因為我已經不想再為你做什麼了
You go on and get yours, 'cause I'm through doing for you.
還扯為我做的事, 你給過我什麼?
What you done for me. What you ever give me?
你的身體, 那個還在跳動的心臟, 臭小子
Them feet. Them bones. That pumping heart, nigger!
我比任何人給過你的都多
Give you more than anybody else ever gonna give you.
你才沒有給過我什麼!
You ain't never gave me nothing!
你只會拖累我
You ain't never done nothing but hold me back,
害怕我會比你有成就!
afraid I was gonna be better than you!
你做過的所有只是想讓我害怕你
All you ever did was try and make me scared of you.
以前你每一次叫我的時候, 我都在顫抖
I used to tremble every time you called my name.
每一次我在屋裏聽到你的腳步聲也是
Every time I heard your footsteps in this house.
總是在想: 如果我這樣做, 爸怎樣反應?
Wondering all the time, "what's pop gonna say if I do this?
他又會怎樣說?
"What's he gonna say if I do that?
如果我打開收音機他又會怎說?
"What's pop gonna say if I turn on the radio?"
媽媽也是! 她試著不去害怕你, 但終究也沒用
And mom, too! She tries, but she's scared of you.
你媽媽與此無關, 她...
Leave your mama out of
this. Your mama ain't got...
真不懂為何你這樣對她後, 她還能接受你
I don't know how she stands you after what you did to her!
我說過, 別把你媽媽混進這事
I told you, leave your mama outta this.
你要怎樣做? 打我嗎?
What are you gonna do? Give me a whupping?
你不能再打我了! 你太老了
You can't whup me no more! You're too old!
你只是個老頭而已
You're just an old man.
臭小子!
Nigger!
你就是這樣, 只是個...
That's what you are. You're just...
對我來說你只是個街上的流氓而已
You're just another nigger on the street to me.
你瘋了! 你知道嗎?
You're crazy! You know that?
對, 去吧
Yeah, go on.
就這樣無視我, 你骨子裏頭是個惡人
Get on away from around me. You got the devil in you.
你只是個瘋老頭! 還說我是惡人
You are just a crazy old man! Talkin' about I got the "devil" in me!
對, 我瘋了
Yeah. I am crazy.
如果你不滾出我的院子
If you don't get the hell out of my yard,
我會讓你看看我有多瘋
I'm gonna show you how crazy I am.
快滾出我的院子!
Now, go on, get the hell out of my yard!
這不是你的院子!
This ain't your yard!
你拿了Gabe叔叔打仗後的賠償
You took Uncle Gabe's money he got from the army
去買這間房子, 然後趕走他了
to buy this house, when you put him out!
快滾出我的院子
Get your black ass out of my yard!
我哪都不去!
I ain't going nowhere!
來啊, 趕走我啊, 我才不怕你
Come on, put me out, i ain't scared of you.
- 那是我的球棒   - 來啊
- That's my bat.   - Come on.
- 放下我的球棒   - 來啊, 趕走我!
- Put my bat down.   - Come on, put me out!
怎麼了? 你要是那麼棒, 趕走我啊!
What's the matter? You so bad. Put me out!
你要有用它的打算
You're gonna have to use it.
你敢對著我拿起球棒, 就要有用它的打算
You want to draw that bat back on me, you're gonna have to use it.
來啊!
Come on!
你要有打死我的打算
You're gonna have to kill me.
要是你敢對著我拿起球棒
You want to draw that bat back on me,
你就要有打死我的打算
you're gonna have to kill me.
來啊
Come on.
你過來, 我教你
Come on. Then I'll show you.
來啊!
Come on!
走吧, 別再在我的房子出現
Go on, get away from around my house.
走啊
Go on.
跟媽媽說我會回來收拾細軟
Tell mama I'll be back for my things.
你的東西會被扔出這藩籬外!
They'll be on the other side of that fence!
感受不到
Can't taste nothing.
我什麼都感受不到
I can't taste nothing.
哈利路亞
Hallelujah!
Hallelujah.
哈利路亞
我什麼都感受不到了
I can't taste nothing no more.
來吧
Come on.
你和我作個了斷吧
It's between you and me now.
來吧, 隨時都行
Come on. Anytime you want.
來吧, 我準備好了
Come on. I be ready for you.
但你別想能全身而退
But I ain't gonna be easy.
Raynell?
- 夫人?   - 你在做什麼?
- Ma'am?   - What you doing?
沒什麼
Nothing.
進來換衣服吧, 你在做什麼?
Get in here and get dressed. What are you doing?
看看它們有沒有長大
See if my garden growed.
我說過它們不會一晚就長大
I told you it ain't gonna grow overnight.
你得耐心點
You got to wait.
對, 但那看起好像永遠不會長大, 該死的!
Yeah, but it look like it ain't never gonna grow, mama. Dag!
我說過, 心急水不沸
I told you, a watched pot never boils.
那可不同, 媽媽
This ain't even no pot, mama.
進來換衣服
Get in here and get dressed.
這不是出外玩的時候, 聽到了嗎?
This ain't no morning to be playing around, you hear me?
明白, 夫人
Yes, ma'am.
再見, 小田園
Bye, garden.
你好, 你想必就是Raynell吧
Hi. I bet your name is Raynell.
你媽媽在家嗎?
Is your mama home?
媽媽, 有個男人找你!
Mama, there's a man down here!
媽媽
Mama!
Cory?
Cory.
Cory, Cory!
Cory. Cory!
- 噢, 我主慈悲!   - Cory
- Oh! Lord have mercy!   - Cory.
你們看看誰來了
Lookee here, y'all.
看他啊
Aww, looka here.
都長大了
Done got all grown up.
別哭, 媽媽, 為何要哭呢?
Don't cry, mama. What you crying about?
只是因為你出現了
I'm just so glad you made it.
嗨, Lyons, 你最近怎了, Bono先生?
Hey, Lyons. How you doing, Mr. Bono?
看看你啊, 老兄
Look at you, man, look at you.
他看上去很威風凜凜吧, Rose? 都是下士了
Don't he look good, Rose? Got on them corporal stripes.
為何現在才來?
What took you so long?
你知道軍隊怎操作的吧, 媽媽
You know how the marines are, mama.
他們得把所有文件檢查清楚
They got to get all their paperwork straight
才讓你做任何事
before they let you do anything.
怎樣都好, 我很高興你趕來了, 他們讓Lyons來
Well, I'm sure glad you made it. They let Lyons come.
你的叔叔Gabe還在醫院內
Your Uncle Gabe's still in the hospital.
他們不知道該否讓他出來
They don't know if they're gonna let him out or not.
我剛跟他們說過話
I talked to them a little while ago.
美國海軍陸戰隊的下士
A corporal in the United States marines.
你爸爸早知道你是軍人的材料
Your daddy knew you had it in you.
他以前總是這樣告訴我
He used to tell me all the time.
他看上去很不錯吧, Bono先生?
Hey, don't he look good, Mr. Bono?
對, 他讓我記起我第一次見到的Troy
Yeah, he reminds me of Troy when I first met him.
我說, Rose
Ah, say, Rose,
Lucille現在在教堂和唱詩班一起
Lucille's down at the church with the choir.
我先去跟那些護柩者說一下
I'm gonna go get the pallbearers lined up.
晚點回來
I'll be back to get you all.
謝謝, Jim
Thanks, Jim.
晚點見, Bono先生
See you, Mr. Bono.
Cory, 看看Raynell
Cory, look at Raynell.
不是很美嗎?
Ain't she precious?
她將來定是個大美人
She's gonna break a whole lot of hearts.
跟你的哥哥打招呼, 這是你的哥哥Cory
Say hello to your brother. This your brother, Cory.
你記得Cory嗎?
You remember Cory?
不記得, 夫人
No, ma'am.
她怎可能記得我, 媽媽
Naw, she don't remember me, mama.
我們有時候會說起你, 她也在的
Oh, well, we talk about you. She heard us talk about you.
這是你的哥哥Cory, 快打招呼
This is your brother, Cory. Say hello.
- 你好   - 你好
- Hi.   - Hi.
所以你就是Raynell吧
So, you're Raynell.
媽媽說了很多關於你的事給我
Mama's told me a lot about you.
讓我煮點早餐給你吃, 別餓壞
Come on, let me fix you some breakfast. Keep up your strength.
我不餓, 媽媽
I ain't hungry, mama.
你可以煮點什麼給我, 我待會進去找你
You can fix me something, Rose. I'll be in there in a minute.
你確定不吃點什麼嗎, Cory?
You sure you don't want nothing, Cory?
我知道他們沒什麼好吃的給你
I know they ain't feeding you right.
不了, 媽媽, 謝謝, 我現在不想吃
No, mama, thanks. I don't feel like eating.
晚點吧
I'll get something later.
Raynell, get up there and get
that dress on like I told you.
我早就知道你能成就大事
I always knew you was gonna make something out of yourself.
你永遠朝著正確的方向走
Your head was always in the right direction.
所以
So,
你打算繼續服役嗎?
you gonna stay in?
讓它成為你的事業? 為軍隊付出20年?
Make it a career? Put in your 20 years?
我不知道, 已經服役六年了, 我想已經足夠了
I don't know. I got six already. I think that's enough.
為美國效力然後早早退休
Stick with Uncle Sam and retire early.
這裏沒有什麼
Ain't nothing out here.
我想Rose跟你說過我發生什麼事了吧
I guess Rose told you about what happened with me.
他們現在讓我在囚犯工廠工作
They got me down at the workhouse.
我自以為偷偷的兌現他人支票很聰明
I thought I was being slick cashing other people's checks.
被判多少年了?
How much time you doing?
三年
They give me three years.
我接受了, 現在只剩九個月
I got that beat now. I ain't got but nine more months.
那也不是件壞事
It ain't so bad.
你能學會如何面對它, 像面對其他事一樣
You learn to deal with it like anything else.
人生不如意事十常八九
"You got to take the crookeds with the straights,"
那就是爸爸的座右銘
that's what papa used to say.
他以前被三振後老是這樣說
He used to say that when he struck out.
我看見過他被連續三次三振
I seen him strike out three times in a row,
再上場時, 他把球打到看台上
and the next time up, he hit the ball over the grandstand.
在霍姆斯特德的棒球場上 [佛羅里達州]
Right out there in Homestead field.
他打到看台上還不滿意
He wasn't satisfied hitting in the seats.
他想打出球場外
He wanted to hit it over everything.
比賽完結後
Then after the game,
有200位觀眾等著與他握手
he had 200 people standing around, waiting to shake his hand.
人生不如意事十常八九
You got to take the crookeds with the straights.
他真與眾不同
Papa was something else.
你還在玩音樂嗎?
You still playing?
Cory, 你知道我不會放棄音樂的
Cory, you know I'm gonna do that.
我跟那裏幾個志同道合的人, 組成了樂隊
We got some fellas down there. We got us a band.
出獄後我們打算繼續一起表演, 但...
We gonna try to stay together when we get out, but...
對
Yeah.
我還在玩音樂
I'm still playing.
它仍然是我有動力活下去的原因
Still helps me get out of bed in the morning.
只要它一天是
As long as it do that,
我就不會放棄它, 更認真對待它
I'm gonna stick with it, try to make some sense out of it.
Lyons, 我煮了蛋給你
Lyons, I got these eggs in a pan.
讓我進去吃點什麼, 老兄
Let me get in here and get these eggs, man.
然後準備讓爸爸入土
Get ready to go bury papa.
你過得怎樣了?
How you doing?
你還好嗎?
You doing all right?
你好
Hi.
你以前睡在我的房間嗎?
You used to sleep in my room?
對, 那以前是我的房間
Yeah, that used to be my room.
那就是爸爸說的, Cory的房間
That's what papa callit. "Cory's room."
你的美式足球還在櫃裏
Got your football in the closet.
Raynell, 快換衣服, 也穿上新的鞋子
Raynell. Get up there, get dressed, and put them good shoes on.
媽媽, 我就不能穿這雙嗎? 那雙新鞋子弄痛我的腳
Mama, can I just wear these? Them others hurt my feet!
那也只會弄痛一會兒而已
Well, they're just gonna have to hurt your feet for a while.
你買的時候
You ain't said they hurt your feet
也沒說它們會弄痛你
when you went down to the store and got 'em.
那時候不痛, 現在我的雙腳都長大了
They didn't hurt then. My feet done got bigger.
別給我頂嘴!
Don't give me no back talk!
快換衣服, 穿上新鞋子
Get up there, get dressed, and put them good shoes on.
這裏沒什麼大改變
Ain't too much changed.
那棒球還吊在樹上
He still got that rag tied to the tree.
他當時在這裏揮棒
He was out here swinging that bat.
我剛想回去屋子內
I was just getting ready to go back in the house.
他一揮, 然後整個人就倒下了
He swung that bat and just fell over.
當他揮棒時, 他看起來好像在笑
Seem like, when he swung it, he stood there with this grin on his face.
下一秒就倒下了
Then he just fell over.
他們來把他送到醫院
They carried him down there to the hospital,
但我知道已經沒有需要了
but I knew there wasn't no need.
不如跟我進去再說?
Why don't you come on in the house?
媽媽, 我有點事要告訴你
Mama, I got something to tell you.
我不知道該怎開口, 但我得告訴你
I don't know how to tell you this, but I got to tell you.
我不會出席爸爸的葬禮
I'm not going to papa's funeral.
小子, 閉嘴
Boy, hush your mouth.
那是你的爸爸!
That's your daddy you talking about!
我不想在這種時候聽到你說這個
I don't want to hear that kind of talk this morning.
我這麼辛苦把你養成這樣的嗎?
I done raised you to come to this?
你健健康康的
You standing there all healthy and grown,
怎麼說你不出席爸爸的葬禮了?
talking about you ain't going to your daddy's funeral?
- 媽媽, 聽著   - 我不想聽, Cory!
- Mama, listen... - I don't want to hear it, Cory!
別再改樣想了
Just get that thought out of your head.
我得向他說不, 就一次, 我得說不
I've got to say no to him. One time in my life, I got to say no.
我不想聽這些!
I don't got to listen to that!
我知道你和你爸爸不和
Now, I know you and your daddy ain't seen eye to eye,
但我不想在這種時候聽到你說出這種話
but I don't have to listen to that kind of talk this morning.
不尊重父親不是作為一個男人該做的事, Cory
Disrespecting your daddy ain't gonna make you a man, Cory.
你得找個方法讓自己接受
You gotta find some way to come to that on your own.
不出席你爸爸的葬禮不會讓你成人的
Not going to your daddy's funeral ain't gonna make you a man.
我以前在這裏的日子
The whole time I was growing up, living in his house,
爸爸就像一道永遠跟著你的黑影
papa was like a shadow that followed you everywhere.
它就像個重擔, 它會侵蝕到你體內
It weighed on you, and it sunk into your flesh.
它會把你緊緊的包著, 不讓你走
It would wrap around you and lay there
直到你分不清哪個才是真正的自己
until you couldn't tell which one was you anymore.
那黑影就一點點的侵蝕到你皮下
That shadow just diggin' into your flesh!
試著佔據你的心, 然後控制你
Trying to crawl in. Trying to live through you.
哪裏都是Troy Maxson的蹤影
Everywhere I looked, I saw Troy Maxson staring right back at me.
在你床下, 又或是在衣櫃內
Hiding under the bed, in the closet.
我只是想說我得找個方法
I'm just saying I got to find a way
去擺脫那個黑影, 媽媽
to get rid of that shadow, mama.
你就像他, 他早已佔據你的心了
You just like him. You got him in you good.
別說我是他, 媽媽
Don't tell me that, mama.
你簡直就是Troy Maxson
You Troy Maxson all over again.
我不想成為Troy Maxson!
I don't want to be Troy Maxson!
我只想做我自己
I just want to be me.
你永遠都會是你自己啊, Cory
You can't be nobody but who you are, Cory.
那黑影只不過是你自己製造出來的
That shadow wasn't nothing but you growing into yourself.
你要麼早晚成為它, 要麼就只接受它的部份
You either got to grow into it, or cut it down to fit you,
但你要生活就得這樣做
but that's all you got to make a life with.
那就是唯一你要跟外面的人比較的東西
That's all you got to measure yourself against the world out there.
你爸爸想你成為和他完全不一樣的人
Your daddy wanted you to be everything he wasn't,
同時間
and at the same time,
他也想你成為他啊
he wanted you to be everything he was.
我不評論他是對還是錯
Now, I don't know if he was right or wrong,
但我知道
but I do know
他本意是想做好事而非傷害你
he meant to do more good than he meant to do harm.
有時候他想碰觸他人, 自己也會受傷
Sometimes, when he touched, he bruised,
有時候他想做好事, 卻成了壞事
and sometimes, when he took me in his arms, he cut.
我最初遇見你爸爸時
When I first met your daddy,
我在想
I thought,
那是個我可以付託終身的人
"here is a man I can lay down with and make a baby."
那就是我對他的第一個想法
That's the first thing I thought when I seen him.
我當時想: Rose Lee
I thought, "Rose Lee,
那是個你可以真誠相對的人
"here's a man you can open yourself up to
然後被他的愛填得滿滿的
"and be filled to bursting!
那是個可以把你心裏空白的位置
"Here's a man that can fill up all them empty spaces
全都補上的人
"you been tipping around the edges of."
當你爸爸進門時
When your daddy walked through the house,
他是...
he was just
那麼的大啊 [形容他獨力承擔起家庭]
so big.
他心裏全都佔滿了 [工作]
He filled it up!
那是我犯下的第一個錯誤
That was my first mistake.
沒讓他在心裏留點位置給我
Not to make him leave some room for me.
但
But
我想要個快樂的家
I wanted a house I could sing in.
你爸爸也給我了
And that's what your daddy gave me.
我不知道該怎樣跟上他的步伐
I didn't know to keep up his strength,
我得犧牲自己
I had to give up little pieces of mine.
我把他的生活當做是我的生活
I took on his life as mine and mixed up the pieces,
以致難以分辨到底那是我的, 還是他的生活 [成全他]
so you couldn't hardly tell which was which.
那是我的選擇, 放棄我的人生
It was my choice. My life.
而我根本不用那樣屈就自己啊
And I didn't have to live it like that,
但那是我作為女人得做的
but that's what life offered me in the way of being a woman,
而我也接受了
and I took it.
我全然接受了
I grabbed it with both hands.
當Raynell來到我們家裏時
And by the time Raynell came into the house...
我不想從別人的不幸上得到快樂
I didn't want to make my blessings off of nobody's misfortune,
但我依然把Raynell當作
but I took on to Raynell like she was
我想要但卻從沒有過的孩子
all them babies I wanted and never had.
就像我可以取回我原本的人生, 即使那麼一點也好
Like I'd been blessed to relive a part of my life.
如果上帝認為有需要的話
And if the lord see fit to keep up my strength,
我會像你爸爸對你那樣對待她
I'm gonna do her exactly how your daddy did you.
我會把我最好的都給她
I'm gonna give her the best of what's in me.
媽媽!
Mama!
Tolliver牧師打來了
Reverend Tolliver on the phone.
你好
Hi.
你在軍隊還是陸戰隊?
You in the army or the marines?
陸戰隊
Marines.
爸爸說你在軍隊, 你認識Blue嗎?
Papa said it was army. You know Blue?
Blue? 誰是Blue?
Blue? Who's blue?
爸爸以前養的狗, 說起他時總會唱起歌來
Papa's dog, what he sing about all the time.
Here, Ring. Yeah, Ring Here
I had an old dog whose name was Blue
You know that Blue was mighty true
You know Blue was a good old dog
Blue treed a 'possum in a hollow log
From that you know Blue's a good old dog
Here, Ring. Yeah, Ring Here
Blue treed a 'possum out on a limb
Blue looked at me and I looked at him
Grabbed that 'possum and put him in a sack
Do fer me, Blue, 'til I get back
Old Blue's feet was big and round
Never 'lowed a 'possum to tech the ground
Old Blue died and I dug his grave
I dug his grave with a silver spade
I let him down with a golden chain
And every link I called his name
Go on Blue you good dog you
一起唱
Come on.
Go on Blue you good dog you
Blue laid down and died like a man
Blue laid down and died...
Now he's treein' 'possums in the promised land
I'm goin' to tell you this jes' to let you know
Old Blue's gone where the good dogs go
Cory, 我們得準備起行了
Cory, we're getting ready to leave now!
聽媽媽的話, 上去換好鞋子
Go upstairs and put your shoes on like mama told you,
然後去爸爸的葬禮
so we can get ready to go to papa's funeral.
好的, 一會見
Okay. I'll be back.
Rose!
嘿, Rose!
Hey, Rose!
- Gabe?   - 我來了, Rose!
- Gabe?   - I'm here! I'm here, Rose!
嘿, Rose, 我來了!
Hey, Rose, I'm here!
- Lyons, 看看是誰!   - 看, Rose?
- Lyons, lookit here!    - See, Rose?
我就知道, 我說過他們會讓他來
I told you. I told you they'd let him come.
- 你好嗎, Gabe叔叔?   - 你好嗎, Gabe叔叔?
- How you doing, Uncle Gabe? - How you doing, Uncle Gabe?
嘿, Rose, 是時候了!
Hey! Hey, Rose, it's time!
是時候叫聖彼得打開天堂之門了
It's time to tell Saint Peter to open the gates.
你準備好了嗎, Troy?
You ready, Troy? Troy, you ready?
我要叫聖彼得打開門了
I'm gonna tell Saint Peter to open the gates.
你快準備好
You get ready now.
Troy!
Troy.
這就對了
That's the way that go.